Prime Minister.
首相。
>> Thank you, Mr. Speaker. With permission,
>> 谢谢您，议长。请允许我，
I'll update the House on my visit last
向议会通报我上周对中国和日本的访问情况，
week to China and Japan where we
以及我们为英国人民取得的成果。
delivered for the British people.
为英国人民取得了实实在在的成果。
>> Mr. Speaker, with events overseas
>> 议长先生，鉴于海外事态
directly impacting on our security and
直接影响到我们的安全和
the cost of living, I made it a founding
生活成本，我将这一点作为本届政府的
principle of this government that after
根本原则，毕竟在经历了多年的孤立主义之后，
years of isolationism,
...
Britain would face outwards once again.
英国将再次面向世界。
>> This was an 18month strategy to rebuild
>> 这是一项为期18个月的战略，旨在重建
our standing
我们的国际地位，
and we have delivered. strengthening our
我们已经取得了成效，加强了我们
US relationship with our world first
与美国的关系，成为世界领先者。
trade deal, resetting our relationship
贸易协议，重塑我们与欧盟的关系
with the EU, striking a groundbreaking
与欧盟重置关系，达成开创性的
FTA with India,
与印度的自由贸易协定，
>> and now thoring our ties with China to
>> 现在加强我们与中国的联系，
put this relationship on a more stable
使这一关系更加稳定。
footing for the long term.
为长期发展奠定基础。
>> Mr. Speaker, China is the second biggest
>> 议长先生，中国是世界第二大经济体，
economy in the world, including Hong
包括香港在内。它是我们的第三大贸易伙伴，
Kong. It's our third biggest trading
支持着37万名英国人就业。
partner, supporting 370,000 British
合作伙伴，支撑着37万个英国
jobs, and it is an undeniable presence
就业机会，这是一个不可否认的存在
in global affairs.
在全球事务中。
It will be impossible to safeguard our
如果不与这一地缘政治现实接触，
national interests without engaging with
我们将无法保障国家利益。
this geopolitical reality.
这一地缘政治现实。
Yet, we inherited a policy from the
然而，我们继承了前届政府的一项政策，
previous government, not of engagement
这不是与中国接触的政策，
with China, but hiding away and sticking
而是选择回避，
their heads in the sand.
把头埋在沙子里。
While our allies developed a more
与此同时，我们的盟友们则采取了更为积极的态度，
sophisticated approach, they let the UK
复杂的策略，他们却让英国落后。
fall behind. We became an outlier.
我们成了一个例外。
Of my three predecessors, none held a
在我的三位前任中，没有一人
single meeting with President Xi
与习近平主席举行过一次会晤，
>> for eight years. No British prime
>> 长达八年之久。没有英国首相…
minister visited China. Eight years of
部长访问了中国。八年来的
missed opportunities.
失去的机遇。
Meanwhile, Mr. Speaker, over that
同时，议长先生，在这段时间内，
period, President Macron visited China
马克龙总统访问了中国三次。
three times.
三倍。
>> German leaders four times. The Canadian
>> 德国领导人已会晤四次。
Prime Minister was there a few weeks
加拿大首相几周前曾到访。
ago. Chancellor Mertz and President
默克尔总理和特朗普总统也将于近期访问。
Trump are both due to visit shortly.
他们即将启程。
They went on their feet
他们站立起来。
>> in this context
>> 在这种情况下
refusing to engage would be a derelic
拒绝参与将是一种玩忽职守
order justice.
司法秩序。
[laughter]
[笑声]
>> Mr. Slug, you will be withdrawing that
>> 斯拉格先生，您将撤回该言论吗
remark.
发言。
>> You withdraw.
>> 你撤回。
>> Thank you. Can we calm it down because
>> 谢谢。我们能否冷静下来，
I'm sure you'll be want to catch my eye
因为我相信你们会想引起我的注意，
and I would like to hear what you've got
而我也愿意听听你们的意见。
to say. So, let's not ruin the
话已至此。让我们不要错失良机。
opportunity. Prime Minister,
首相，
>> Mr. Speaker, in this context, refusing
>> 议长先生，在此情境下，拒绝参与将是一种失职，
to engage would be a dereliction of
放弃责任，
duty, leaving British interests on the
使英国利益处于不利地位。
sideline. And incredibly, some in this
旁观。而令人难以置信的是，本院中仍有人主张这种做法。
house still advocate that approach. But,
但是，议长先生，领导者不会选择回避。
Mr. Speaker, leaders do not hide.
相反，我们积极参与。
Instead, we engage. And we do so on our
并且我们是在自己的条件下参与，因为，正如我们的盟友一样，
own terms because, like our allies, we
我们……
understand that engagement makes us
我们理解，积极参与使我们更加强大。
stronger.
>> 议长先生，保护我们的国家安全是不可谈判的底线。我们对来自……的威胁保持清醒的认识。
>> Mr. Speaker, protecting our national
>> 议长先生，维护国家安全
security is non-negotiable. We're
是不容妥协的。我们
cleareyed about the threats coming from
对来自...的威胁保持清醒认识
China in that regard and we will never
在这方面，我们对中国的态度坚定不移，
waver in our efforts to keep the British
我们将始终不懈努力，保障英国人民的安全。
people safe. That is why we've given our
正因如此，我们赋予了安全部门
security services the updated powers and
更新后的权力和工具，
tools that they need to tackle foreign
以应对外国威胁。
espionage activity wherever they find it
无论在哪里发现间谍活动，我们都将予以打击
and tackle malicious cyber activity as
并且同样应对恶意网络活动。
well.
>> 但是事实是，议长先生，我们可以同时做两件事。我们既能保护
>> But the fact is, Mr. Speaker, we can do
>> 但事实是，议长先生，我们可以
two things at once. we can protect
双管齐下。我们可以保护
ourselves whilst also finding ways to
在坚持自身利益的同时，也寻求合作的途径。
cooperate. And it was in that spirit
正是基于这种精神，
that we made this visit.
我们才进行了此次访问。
>> I had extensive discussions over many
>> 我与习近平主席、李总理进行了长时间的深入讨论，
hours with President Xi, Premier Lee,
多个小时的会谈，内容广泛，
and other senior leaders. The
与其他高级领导人会晤。
discussions were positive and
讨论积极且富有建设性。
constructive.
我们涵盖了从战略稳定到贸易的全部议题，
We covered the full range of issues from
以及……
strategic stability to trade and
贸易关系的战略稳定性，以及
investment, opening a direct channel of
投资，开辟一条直接沟通渠道
communication to deliver in the national
以实现国家利益，
interest, enabling us to raise frank
使我们能够坦率地提出关切，
concerns about activities that impact
针对影响
our national security at the most senior
我们国家安全的活动，直接向最高层反映
levels of the Chinese system. We agreed
中方体制各级别。我们同意
to intensify dialogue on cyber issues
加强在网络问题上的对话，
and we agreed a new partnership on
并达成了一项关于气候与自然的新伙伴关系，
climate and nature providing much needed
为这一至关重要的问题提供急需的
global leadership on this vital issue.
全球领导力。
And Mr. Speaker, I raised a number of
议长先生，我提出了若干
areas of difference which matter deeply
对本国极为重要的分歧领域。
to this country.
我提到了吉米·李的案子，
I raised the case of Jimmy Lie and
并呼吁释放他，
called for his release,
呼吁释放他，
>> making clear the strength of feeling in
>> 明确表达本院的强烈感情。
this house. Those discussions will
相关讨论将继续进行，
continue and my right honorable friend
我的尊敬的同僚外交大臣
the foreign secretary is in touch with
正与李先生的家属保持联系，
Mr. Li's family to provide further
以提供进一步的支持。
briefing.
简报。
I raised our human rights concerns in
我提出了我们对新疆和西藏的人权关切。
Shinyang and Tibet.
我们讨论了台湾问题、地区更广泛的稳定、伊朗以及中东局势。
We discussed Taiwan, wider regional
（此条为空，原文无内容）
stability, Iran and the Middle East.
I called on China to end economic
我呼吁中国停止对俄罗斯战争行动的经济支持，
support for Russia's war effort,
>> 包括那些提供双重用途技术的公司，
>> including companies providing dual use
>> 并且我敦促他们发挥影响力，
technologies
>> 以促使局势改善。
>> and I urged them to use their influence
>> 我敦促他们利用其影响力
on Putin to push for the muchneeded
呼吁普京推动迫切需要的
ceasefire in Ukraine.
乌克兰停火。
And Mr. Speaker, I also raised the fact
议长先生，我还提到，
that members of this house have been
本院部分议员已被中国当局制裁。
sanctioned by the Chinese authorities.
受到中国当局制裁。
In response, the Chinese have now made
作为回应，中国方面现已明确表示，
it clear that all such restrictions on
对议员们的所有此类限制
parliamentarians no longer apply.
不再适用。
>> And I want to be clear,
>> 我想明确指出，
>> this was not the result of a trade.
>> 这并非任何交易的结果。
>> Exactly.
>> 完全正确。
>> Yes, members will want to see more. I
>> 是的，议员们希望看到更多，我理解这一点。
understand that.
>> 但这正是关键所在。
>> But that is precisely the point.
>> 八年来对中国的忽视所带来的结果是…
>> Ignoring China for eight years achieved
>> 无视中国八年，并没有实现
nothing.
毫无进展。
This step is an early indication,
这一步是一个初步的迹象，
not the sum total, of the kind of
并非全部成果，
progress that this sort of engagement
但显示出此类接触
can achieve through leaderto-leer
通过领导人间的直接对话所能取得的进展。
discussion on sensitive issues to stand
关于敏感问题的讨论应当坚持立场
up for British interests.
以维护英国利益为重。
Mr. Speaker, my visit was also about
议长先生，我此次访问的目的之一，
creating new opportunities for British
也是为英国企业创造新的机遇，
businesses to deliver jobs and growth
以推动就业和经济增长。
for the British people. We took with us
为了英国人民，我们带去了
a brilliant delegation of nearly 60
一支由近60家企业和文化巨头组成的杰出代表团，
businesses and cultural powerhouses, the
他们是英国最优秀的代表，
very best of British as an embodiment of
体现了这个国家所能提供的最佳价值。若是
what this country has to offer. If
这个国家所能提供的机遇。如果
anyone's in doubt as to why this
如果有人对这件事的重要性存有疑问，
matters, I urge them to spend a few
我敦促他们花几分钟时间，
minutes with any one of those
与那些企业中的任何一家交流。
businesses. They will tell you about the
他们会告诉你那里蕴藏的
incredible potential there and the
巨大潜力，以及…
importance of getting out there and
积极开拓市场的重要性
accessing the market. And we made
并进入市场。我们取得了
significant progress paving the way to
重大进展，为
open the Chinese market for British
打开中国市场铺平了道路，促进英国
exports, including our worldleading
出口，包括我们在全球领先的领域
services sector. We secured a 30-day
服务业领域。我们为所有英国人争取到了30天的
visa free travel for all Brits,
免签证旅行，包括商务旅客。我们获得了
including business travelers. We secured
中国同意将关税从10%降至5%。
China's agreement to harvey tariffs from
中国同意将关税从
10% to 5%.
10%降至5%。
>> This is worth 250 million pounds the UK
>> 这对英国来说，在未来五年内价值2.5亿英镑。
over the next 5 years. over there.
就在那里。
>> A significant win for our iconic whiskey
>> 这是我们标志性威士忌产业，尤其是苏格兰的重大胜利。
industry, particularly in Scotland.
>> 议长先生，这一降低的关税带来了……
>> And Mr. Speaker, that lower tariff comes
>> 议长先生，这一关税下调
into force today. In total, we secured
今天生效。我们共获得了
2.3 billion pounds in market access
23亿英镑的市场准入收益，
wins, including for financial services,
包括金融服务领域，
2.2 billion pounds in export deals for
为英国企业争取了22亿英镑的出口订单，
British companies, and hundreds of
以及数以百计的…
millions worth of new investments.
数百万英镑的新投资。
>> In addition, Mr. Speaker, we agreed to
>> 此外，议长先生，我们同意
work together in some key areas of law
在若干关键执法领域开展合作。
enforcement.
去年，大约60%的所有小型船只
Last year, around 60% of all smallboat
去年，约60%的小船
engines used by smuggling gangs came
走私团伙使用的引擎来自中国。
from China. So, we struck a border
因此，我们签署了一项边境安全协议，
security pact to enable joint law
以便开展联合执法行动，
enforcement action to disrupt that
旨在从源头上打击该供应链。
supply at source. We also agreed to
我们还同意…
scale up removals of those with no right
加大对无权留在英国者的遣返力度
to be in the United Kingdom and to work
并携手合作，严厉打击合成类阿片类药物的供应。
together to crack down on the supply of
我们将继续推进相关工作
synthetic opioids.
（原文无内容，此处保持空行）
We will continue to develop our work
across all these areas.
涉及所有这些领域。
>> Because Mr. Speaker, this is the start
>> 议长先生，因为这是一个过程的开始， 而非结束。
of the process, not the end of it.
>> 我的访问不仅仅是为了带回这些协议。它的意义在于
>> My visit was not just about coming back
with these agreements. It was about the
>> 我的访问不仅仅是为了带回这些协议。它的意义在于
wider question of setting this
关于将这一关系置于更优轨道的更广泛问题
relationship on a better path which
这将使我们能够以一种前届政府未能做到的方式
allows us to deal with issues and seize
处理问题并抓住机遇。
opportunities in a way that the previous
（原文无内容）
government failed to do.
>> Finally, Mr. Speaker, let me say a word
>> 最后，议长先生，请允许我谈一句关于我在东京的会晤。
about my meetings in Tokyo.
日本依然是我们最亲密的盟友之一。
Japan remains one of our closest allies.
我们共同是《全面与进步跨太平洋伙伴关系协定》（CPTPP）中的领先经济体，
Together, we're the leading economies in
——
the CPTP,
CPTPP，
partners in the G7, the G20, and the
七国集团、二十国集团以及志愿联盟的合作伙伴，
Coalition of the Willings, and they are
他们是英国在美国和欧洲之外最大的外来投资者。
the UK's largest inward investor outside
因此，我与他们进行了极为富有成效的会谈，
the United States and Europe. So, I had
这次会谈内容丰富，成果显著。
an extremely productive meeting with the
（原文第5条不完整，无法翻译）
Prime Minister as we set out our shared
首相，正如我们阐述的共同优先事项，
priorities to build an even deeper
旨在未来几年内建立更加深厚的伙伴关系。
partnership in the years to come. That
这包括携手合作，促进和平与
includes working together for peace and
安全，支持乌克兰，
security, supporting Ukraine as we work
与此同时我们努力…
for a just and lasting peace, and
为实现公正持久的和平，
deepening our cooperation in cutting
以及深化我们在尖端防务生产领域的合作，
edge defense production, including
包括通过全球联合防务合作计划（GCAP）。
through GCAP.
我们讨论了如何促进增长，
We discussed how we can boost growth and
并且…
economic resilience by developing our
通过发展我们的经济韧性，
cooperation first in tech and innovation
首先加强在科技与创新领域的合作，
where where we are both leaders.
因为我们双方都是该领域的领导者。
second in energy where Japan is a major
其次是在能源领域，日本是英国的重要投资者，
investor in the UK and third in trade
第三是在贸易领域。
where we're working together to maintain
我们正携手合作，维护
the openness and stability that our
我们企业赖以生存的开放性与稳定性。
businesses depend on. That includes
这包括
expanding the CPTP and deepening its
扩大《全面与进步跨太平洋伙伴关系协定》（CPTPP），并深化其
cooperation with the EU.
与欧盟的合作。
We will take all of this forward, Mr.
议长先生，针对上述所有事项，我们将继续推进，
Speaker, when I welcome the prime
议长先生，届时我将欢迎首相于今年晚些时候在切克斯会面。
minister to checkers later this year.
议长先生，今年晚些时候我将欢迎首相在切克斯会面。
So, Mr. Speaker, this is Britain back at
议长先生，这就是英国终于重返最高决策层，面向世界，
the top table at last, facing outward,
replacing incoherence and isolationism
用务实的参与取代混乱和孤立主义，
with pragmatic engagement,
用务实的参与，
replacing naive posturing with the
用国家利益取代幼稚的姿态，
national interest. In dangerous times,
在危险时期，
we're using our full strength and reach
我们正在发挥我们的全部力量和影响力。
on the world stage to deliver a growth
在国际舞台上推动增长
and security for the British people. And
保障英国人民的安全。
I commend this statement to the house,
我向议会推荐这份声明，
the leader of the office.
由政府首脑发表。
THANK YOU, MR. SPEAKER, and I thank the
谢谢您，议长先生，我也感谢…
prime minister for advanced sight of his
首相应提前通报他的声明，
statement, but it is utterly
但他开篇却完全令人谴责，
reprehensible that he began it by
指责前届政府实行孤立主义，
accusing the previous government of
这是极其不当的。
isolationism.
（此句为上一句的延续，故合并翻译）
The same conservative government Oh, the
同一个保守党政府，哦，
business secretary is laughing. Just
商务大臣正在笑。只是
just that we'll tell him. The same
只是我们会告诉他。同一个
conservative government that led the
保守党政府，在应对入侵事件上
world in our response to the invasion of
领导了世界。
Ukraine that signed a vital strategic
乌克兰签署了一项重要的战略联盟
alliance in Orcus. The the business
在奥库斯。商务大臣正在询问我们签署了多少自由贸易协定
secretary is asking how many FTAs we
这是英国迄今为止最大的后脱欧贸易协议——全面与进步跨太平洋伙伴关系协定（CPTPP），
signed Britain's biggest postbacked
它将我们与合作伙伴的关系更加紧密，
trade deal the CPTP bringing us closer
使我们更接近……
to the 11 Indo-Pacific nations including
致包括日本在内的11个印太国家。
Japan. He asks I know about that deal
他问我是否了解那项协议，
because I signed it myself.
因为那是我亲自签署的。
And so I welcome the prime minister's
因此，我欢迎首相在加强与我们合作方面所做的努力，
efforts to collaborate more with our
——
long-standing ally Japan. But let's turn
长期盟友日本。但让我们转向中国。
to China. Of course, Britain should
当然，英国应当与中国接触。
engage with China. Even though the
尽管财政大臣未被允许前往，
chancellor wasn't allowed to go, even
尽管他们是一个威权国家，
though they are an authoritarian state
——
who seek to undermine our interests,
试图破坏我们利益的人，
even though they spy on us, sometimes
即使他们对我们进行间谍活动，有时甚至
within the walls of this building,
就发生在这座大楼内，
>> even though they fund regimes around the
>> 即使他们资助世界各地对我国怀有敌意的政权，
world hostile to our country, they are a
他们仍然是一个…
fact of life, a global power, and an
这是一个不争的事实，是一个全球性大国，
economic reality. So, let me be clear.
也是一个经济现实。所以，请允许我明确指出。
It is not the prime minister engaging
我们并不反对首相与中国接触。
with China that we take issue with. What
我们批评的是他那种软弱无力的态度，
we are criticizing is his supine and
以及他对……
short-termist approach.
短视的做法。
I am sure the prime minister I'm sure
我相信首相，我相信
the prime minister means well, but his
首相本意良好，但他的
negotiating tactic has always been to
谈判策略一直是
give everything away in the hope that
事事让步，希望能够…
people will be nice to him in return.
人们也会因此对他友善相待。
Before the prime minister even got on
在首相甚至登机之前，
the plane, he'd already shown that he
他已经表明自己会不惜一切代价，
would do anything to demonstrate his
以展示他与中国的良好关系。
good relationship with China. But China
但是中国方面
uses every interaction to improve its
利用每一次互动来提升自身的地位。
own position.
>> 首相看起来很享受他的这次访问。事实上，对于这样一位男子来说，
>> The prime minister looked like he
这次访问看起来就像梦想成真一般，
enjoyed his trip. In fact, it looked
很享受他的旅行。事实上，这看起来
like a dream come true for a man who was
就像梦想成真，对于一个曾经
virtually a communist most of his life.
他几乎一生都是共产主义者。
[laughter]
【笑声】
>> But apart from the
>> 但是，除了……
[cheering]
【欢呼声】
Mr. Speaker, apart from the Lab Vubu
议长先生，除了工党……
doll in his suitcase, and I hope he's
他行李箱里带着一个玩偶，我希望他已经检查过有没有窃听器，
checked it for bugs, he has come back
他几乎一无所获地回来了。
with next to nothing.
>> 我们都希望苏格兰威士忌的关税更低。但如果首相
>> We all want cheaper tariffs for Scottish
>> 我们都希望苏格兰威士忌的关税
whiskey. But if the prime minister
更低。但如果首相
bothered to speak to the whiskey
如果他像我两周前那样，费心与威士忌行业对话，
industry like I did two weeks ago, he
他就会知道他们真正需要的是
would know that what they really need is
更廉价的能源和更低的税负。
cheaper energy and lower taxes.
>> 他还得到了什么？免签证旅行。
>> What else did he get? Visa free travel.
>> 他还得到了什么？免签旅行。
China already offers this to other
中国已经向其他国家提供了这一待遇。
countries. It's not big enough for a
这不足以成为首相访问的理由。
prime ministerial visit.
>> 但是，议长先生，最糟糕的事情，
>> But the worst thing, Mr. Speaker, the
最糟糕的事情就是首相……
worst thing was the prime minister
最糟糕的是首相
claiming a glorious triumph with the
声称自己取得了辉煌的胜利，
lifting of sanctions on four
因为对四名保守党议员的制裁被解除，
conservative MPs as if he'd done us a
仿佛他是在帮了我们一个忙。
favor. Let me tell him, those MPs were
让我告诉他，那些议员之所以被制裁，
sanctioned because they stood UP TO
是因为他们敢于反抗。
CHINA. THEY THEY STOOD UP AGAINST human
中国。他们站出来反对侵犯人权的行为。
rights abuses. They stood up against a
他们反对一个国家以一种他不敢为的方式监视我们的议员。
country spying on our MPs in a way that
那些人不想去中国。
he wouldn't dare. Those people don't
中国人知道…
want to go to China. The Chinese know
（原文未完，无法翻译）
that. They know that they are giving him
他们知道他们给予他的东西
something that costs absolutely nothing.
完全没有任何代价。
Why can't the Brit British prime
英国首相为什么看不到这一点？
minister see that? And I say to you, Mr.
我对您说，议长先生，以及全体议员，正如……
Speaker, and the whole house, like with
（后文未完，无法继续翻译）
the Chaos Islands, the prime minister
混乱群岛，首相
has been played.
已经被操纵。
>> China is about to build an enormous spy
>> 中国即将在伦敦市中心建立一个巨大的间谍中心。
hub in the center of London. A ransom he
这是他在登台之前不得不支付的赎金。
had to pay before he could even get on
他甚至还未能登台。
the plane.
飞机。
>> I would never allow Britain to be held
>> 我绝不会允许英国被那样挟持。
over a barrel like that. Yet again, the
首相再次将我们国家谈判至一个更弱的地位，
prime minister has negotiated our
在……
country into a weaker position in the
（原文未完，无法翻译）
world. His entire economic policy is to
世界。他的整个经济政策就是
tax business more, regulate them harder,
加重对企业的税收，强化监管，
and make energy so expensive that we
使能源价格高昂到我们不得不去工业化。
de-industrialize. And then we can import
然后我们只能进口
Chinese wind turbines, Chinese solar
中国的风力发电机、中国的太阳能设备。
panels, Chinese batteries for electric
太阳能电池板、中国制造的电动车电池，
vehicles, all manufactured in a country
全部产自一个每隔一周就建设一座燃煤电厂的国家。
that is building a coal fired power
他是否就此与他们交谈过？
station every other week. Did he speak
他的首席……
to them about that? What did his chief
（后文未完）
his trip achieve for Jimmy Lie? Nothing.
这次访问为吉米·赖带来了什么成果？毫无成效。
Did China promise to stop fueling
中国是否承诺停止为普京在乌克兰的战争机器提供支持？
Putin's war machine in Ukraine? Doesn't
听起来并非如此。
sound like it. What did this trip
这次访问为那些正在遭受苦难的人们带来了什么成果？
achieve for the weaguers who are being
（原文未完，无法翻译）
enslaved? Absolutely nothing. Have China
被奴役了吗？绝对没有。中国是否
agreed to stop their relentless cyber
同意停止他们无休止的网络攻击？
attacks. Have they? We all know the
他们同意了吗？我们都知道答案。
answer to that. The reality is that
事实是，
China showed its strength and Britain
中国展现了其实力，而英国…
was pushed around literally.
他确实被人任意摆布。
It is no wonder, Mr. Speaker, that
议长先生，难怪
President Xi praised the Labor Party
习近平主席赞扬工党，
because the Conservatives stood up for
因为保守党为英国挺身而出。
Britain. We don't get pushed around.
我们绝不任人摆布。
>> Britain is a great trading nation. Of
>> 英国是一个伟大的贸易国家。
course, we should engage with other
当然，我们应该与其他国家交往，甚至是敌对国家。
countries, even hostile ones.
>> 请安静。凯尔先生，您曾对我说过，去中国时会表现得很好。
>> Order. Mr. Kyle, you said to me when you
>> 秩序。凯尔先生，你曾对我说，当你
going to China how well you will behave.
去中国时，你会表现得多么得体。
Oh, you owe me a big thank you. You're
哦，你应该好好感谢我。
not showing it today. Come here.
可你今天一点也不领情。过来。
Mr. Speaker, I'm not worried about the
议长先生，我并不担心商务大臣。
business secretary. The entire business
整个商业界都认为他是个笑柄，
community thinks he's a joke and doesn't
并不把他当回事。
know what he's talking about.
知道他在说什么。
>> So, as I was saying, of course, we
>> 正如我刚才所说，当然，我们
should engage with other countries, even
应该与其他国家交往，甚至是
hostile ones. But we need to do so with
敌对国家。但我们需要睁大眼睛，
our eyes open and from a position of
并且立于有利地位去进行交往。
strength, and that requires a prime
实力，而这需要一位首相和政府将国家利益置于首位。
minister and a government that puts our
>> 首相，
national interest first.
>> 议长先生，请允许我确认我是否理解正确，
>> Prime Minister,
>> 首相，
>> Mr. Speaker, let me see if I understand
>> 议长先生，让我看看我是否理解
her position. This is the leader of the
她的立场。这是反对党领袖所持的立场，
opposition who said we should empty
她曾表示我们应该空缺
chair the most important NATO summit for
多年来最重要的北约峰会的主席席位，
years,
>> 她不会出席七国集团峰会，
>> who wouldn't turn up to the G7,
>> 他甚至不愿出席七国集团（G7）峰会，
>> who would rip up our valuable trade
>> 谁将撕毁我们与美国、印度和欧盟之间宝贵的贸易协议，
deals with the US, India, and the EU.
>> 这是反对党领袖，他曾将格陵兰描述为次要议题，
>> This is the leader of the opposition who
>> 这就是反对党领袖，他曾
characterized Greenland as a second
将格陵兰岛形容为次要
order issue,
问题，
>> then undermined the government's
>> 然后削弱了政府在主权问题上的立场。
position on sovereignty.
当谈及中国时，她的政策是视而不见，无法施加任何影响。
And when it comes to China, her policy
在一个动荡不安的
is to stick her head in the sand, unable
就是把头埋在沙子里，无法
to influence anything. In a volatile
施加任何影响。在一个动荡的
world, that is not policy. That's an
世界，这不是政策。那是
abdication of responsibility.
责任的放弃。
>> No wonder her front are leaving in
>> 难怪她的前线人员纷纷离开。
droves.
>> 议长先生，她谈到了…
>> And Mr. Speaker, she talks of the
>> 议长先生，她谈到了
embassy. China's had an embassy in the
大使馆。中国自1877年起就在英国设立了大使馆。
UK since 1877.
中国大使馆自1877年以来一直驻扎在英国。
is currently spread across seven sides.
目前分布在七个地点。
>> The leader of the opposition is so busy
>> 反对党领袖忙于维系党内团结，
trying to hold her party together, she's
她……
clearly not read the letter
显然没有读过这封信
[cheering and laughter] to security and
[欢呼与笑声] 关于安全和
intelligence services.
情报部门。
But Mr. Speaker, she claims great
但是议长先生，她声称对此非常关注
interest
。
in the China embassy. She was offered an
在中国大使馆。她被邀请参加一次
invite for a privy council briefing on
有关该问题的枢密院简报会。
the issue. What did she do? She chose
她怎么做了？她选择了
not to attend.
不出席。
>> Mr. Speaker, that's a dereliction of
>> 议长先生，那是玩忽职守，
duty.
责任。
Even worse, what did she do? She sent in
更糟糕的是，她做了什么？她派遣了
her place the member for Cudon South,
库登南选区的议员代替她，
the shadow home secretary. That is a
也就是影子内政大臣。那是
double dereliction of Jupy.
对职责的双重失职。
>> Instead of taking up a privy council
>> 她没有接受枢密院的简报，
brief and she took up a megaphone on the
而是在大使馆外的街头拿起了扩音器，
streets outside the embassy,
>> 我将我的政党从抗议党转变为执政党。她是
>> I changed my party from a party of
（原文第4条与第5条合并翻译）
protest to a party of power. She's
———（第5条内容不完整，无法单独翻译）
rapidly going in the opposite direction.
正在迅速朝着相反的方向发展。
And her her reply this afternoon seems
而她今天下午的回应似乎是，
to be that we should engage with China
我们应该与中国接触，
but not engage with China.
但又不应该与中国接触。
>> That what we should do instead of
>> 这就是我们应该做的，取代……
leaderto leader discussions where we
领导人之间的会谈，我们
raise all the opportunities and the
提出所有的机遇以及
difficult issues each and every one of
每一个棘手的问题，
them instead of those leader meeting
而不是那些领导人之间的会议，
leader to leader meetings should get a
领导人之间的会谈应当获得一个…
bag of sand and put her head in it and
把头埋进沙袋里，
influence absolutely nothing. They're so
毫无影响力。 他们对国际事务极不认真。
unserious about world affairs. Chair for
第一委员会主席，戴夫·埃姆利·索尔。
First Committee, Dave Emley Thor.
>> 非常感谢，议长先生。嗯，我想要…
>> Very much, Mr. Speaker. Um, I'd like to
>> 非常感谢，议长先生。嗯，我想
thank the Prime Minister for his
感谢首相的陈述，
statements and I'm pleased to see that
我很高兴看到他的访问进展顺利。
his trip went so well. This morning, I
今天上午，我与苏格兰威士忌协会取得了联系，
was in touch with the Scotch Whiskey
他们希望我转达他们的意见。
Association who want me to convey their
协会，他们希望我转达他们的
congratulations to the Prime Minister
祝贺首相
for securing reduced tariff with China.
成功与中国达成关税减让协议。
But there is, of course, more work
但当然，仍有更多工作需要完成。
needed. A prime minister's job is never
首相的职责永远不会结束。
done. Um the biggest overseas market for
嗯，最大的海外市场是…
whiskey is of course the US where the
当然，威士忌主要指的是美国市场，
tariff is still too high. So can the
那里的关税依然过高。
prime minister confirm that this will
首相能否确认，
not be the end of the support that he
他对苏格兰威士忌的支持不会就此终止，
will give to the scotch whiskey um
而是会继续给予支持？
industry and will continue to be an
工业领域，并将继续为其发声。
advocate for them.
>> 是的，我可以确认，我们将继续与美国合作，当然还有我们达成的印度协议。
>> Yes, I can cons uh confirm that uh we're
>> 是的，我可以确...呃...确认我们正在
continuing to work with the US and of
继续与美国合作，当然还有
course uh the India deal that we secured
我们达成的印度协议
will have an impact on tariffs for
这也将对威士忌的关税产生影响。
whiskey as well.
威士忌的关税也将受到影响。
Okay.
好的。
>> Leader of the Liberal Democrat, Sir Ed
>> 自由民主党领袖，埃德爵士·戴夫。
Dav.
>> Thank you, Mr. Speaker. And with your
>> 谢谢您，议长先生。
indulgence, can I start by paying
如果您允许，我想先表达敬意，
tribute to my friend Jim Wallace, one of
向我的朋友吉姆·华莱士致敬，他是
the great Scottish liberals, and offer
苏格兰伟大的自由主义者之一，
our thoughts and prayers to his family
并向他的家人表达我们的思念与祈祷。
and many friends. Jim devoted his life
和许多朋友。吉姆毕生致力于公共服务，
to public service, his Christian faith,
他的基督教信仰，
and the cause of liberalism.
以及自由主义事业。
But, Mr. Speaker, his judgment wasn't
但是，议长先生，他的判断并非总是无可挑剔。因为正是吉姆
always impeccable. for it was Jim who
...
gave me my first job in politics.
是他给了我在政治上的第一份工作。
[laughter]
[笑声]
>> We as opposed to your last.
>> 我们是相对于你的上一任而言。
>> We will miss him.
>> 我们会怀念他的。
>> Turning to the statement, can I thank
>> 现在转向声明环节，我要感谢...
the prime minister for advanced sight of
首相提前获悉此事吗？
it? I listen to the Conservative leader
我听了保守党领袖的发言，
whose position now seems to be to oppose
他现在的立场似乎是反对与
trade with the world's biggest
世界最大经济体的贸易。
economies. So much for global Britain.
这就是所谓的全球英国。
>> But with Mr. Speaker, with President
>> 但是，议长先生，
Trump threatening tariffs again just
由于首相的访问，特朗普总统再次威胁要征收关税，
because of the prime minister's trip,
仅仅因为首相的这次行程，
with Vladimir Putin still murdering
俄罗斯总统普京仍在乌克兰杀害平民，
civilians in Ukraine, now more than
现在已有超过…
ever, the United Kingdom must forge much
英国必须与那些与我们共享价值观、
closer alliances with nations who share
信奉自由贸易、
our values, our belief in free trade,
并致力于共同防御的国家建立更加紧密的联盟。
and our commitment to our mutual
但中国并不具备这些条件。
defense. But China is none of those. The
防务。但中国不属于其中任何一类。
prime minister's main focus should be on
首相的主要关注点应当是
the closest possible ties with our
与我们欧洲邻国、
European neighbors, our Commonwealth
英联邦盟友以及像日本和
allies, and our friends like Japan and
韩国这样的朋友保持尽可能紧密的联系。
Korea. So once again, he has made the
因此，他再次表明了立场，
wrong choice. However, unlike the
错误的选择。然而，与保守党不同，
Conservative Party, we think he was
我们认为他当时前去接触是正确的。
right to go and engage. But just like
但正如对待特朗普总统一样，
with President Trump, he approached
他与习近平主席的接触是出于弱势地位，
President Xi from a position of weakness
而非强势立场。
instead of position of strength,
不是以强势立场，
promising him a super embassy here in
承诺在伦敦设立一个超级大使馆，
London in return for relatively meager
以换取中国相对微薄的让步。
offers from China. He rightly raised the
他正确地提出了吉米·赖的案件，
case of Jimmy Lie, whose children fear
其子女对此深感担忧。
for his health after 5 years held in
关于他在被囚禁五年后的健康状况。
captivity. So will the prime minister
那么，首相能否告诉我们，
tell us what she said to give him
她说了些什么，
confidence that Mr. Lie is now more
以增强他对李先生现在更有可能获释的信心？
likely to be released?
有可能被释放吗？
Did he also challenge Shei over the
他是否也就英国境内无辜香港人的头上悬赏问题质问了谢伊？
bounties on the heads of innocent Hong
关于中国对无辜香港人在英国境内悬赏的行为，
Kongers here in the United Kingdom? All
以及所有关于中国多年来入侵首相府官员手机的揭露，
the revelations that China hacked the
这些问题他是否都提出了质疑？
phones of number 10 officials for years.
（注：原文第4、5句内容连贯，翻译时合并处理。）
In other words, did he stand up for
换句话说，他这次是否为英国挺身而出？
Britain this time? And yet again, Mr.
然而，议长先生，首相再次不得不在一次出访中，
Speaker, the prime minister had to spend
花费时间回应有关那名卑劣恋童癖者的揭露，
time on a foreign trip responding to
以及
revelations about the vile pedophile and
…（后续内容未提供，无法翻译）
sex trafficker Jimmy Epstein and his
性贩卖者吉米·爱泼斯坦及其
relationship with Lord Mandlesson. The
与曼德尔森勋爵的关系。
prime minister has rightly said that
首相已正确表示，
Manslson should resign from the other
曼德尔森应当辞去上议院议员职务。
place. But since he hasn't, will he back
但既然他没有辞职，首相是否会支持...
a simple piece of legislation to strip
一项简单的立法，剥夺他的贵族身份？
him of his periage? Surely this house
这个议会明天肯定能够通过它。
could pass it tomorrow.
>> 部长，
>> Minister,
>> 我能否先表达我深切的
>> can I start by offering my deep
（后续内容未提供，无法翻译）
condolences on behalf of the government
代表政府表示哀悼
in relation to Lord Wallace? Um, he was
关于华莱士勋爵？嗯，他是
a kind and decent man. uh and I know
一位善良而正直的人。嗯，我知道
he'll be sorely missed uh on the Liberal
自由民主党席位上将深切怀念他，嗯，愿他安息
Democrat benches and may he rest in
（原文未完，无法翻译）
peace. Um in relation to uh the approach
和平。嗯，关于对华政策的方针，
to China, of course, we need to build
当然，我们需要与关键伙伴建立
stronger alliances uh with our key
更加牢固的联盟，
partners and that's what we have been
这正是我们一直在做的，尤其是与欧盟。
doing particularly with the EU. But he's
但是他……
wrong. It's not a choice between doing
错误。这并不是在采取某种行动与与中国接触之间的选择，
that and engaging with China. One can do
两者是可以兼顾的，而这正是我们正在做的。
both and that is what we're doing. And I
我认为，更重要的是关注那些存在机遇的领域。
think it's more important where there
认为更重要的是，在有
are opportunities
机遇的地方
and sensitive and really important
这是一个敏感且极为重要的问题
disagreements
存在分歧
to have a meeting to discuss them
需要召开会议进行讨论
because the House is violently agreeing
因为下议院一致强烈认同
that there are issues that need to be
有一些亟需解决的问题
discussed. The difference between us is
已经讨论过了。我们之间的分歧在于
we think that having a leader to leader
我们认为举行领导人之间的会晤来讨论这些问题
meeting to discuss those issues is
比起回避问题要更有效，
better than sticking your head in the
也就是比起把头埋在沙子里不理会问题，
sand if you really want to influence
如果你真想施加影响的话。
this. So we can do both. uh in relation
因此，我们可以兼顾两者。关于他提出的那些问题，
to uh the points he raised. Yes, I did
是的，我确实提到了吉米·李的案件，
raise the case of Jimmy Lie and we've
我们现在已经与他的家属就此进行了沟通。
now spoken to his family about that
关于那次讨论，
discussion. Uh yes, I did raise the case
是的，我确实提到了该案件。
of Hong Kong. I raised a number of human
关于香港的问题。我提出了多项人权议题，正如我所列举的那样。
rights issues as I listed. The point was
关键在于，通过亲自出席会议，参与一对一的领导人级别辩论，
by being in the room having the debate
有机会直接提出这些问题。
onetoone with the leader at leader
领导人之间的面对面交流，
level, it was possible to raise those
使得提出这些议题成为可能。
issues. There is frankly no point
诸多问题。坦率地说，
standing in this house shouting and
如果你不准备坐下来讨论，
screaming about issues if you're not
在本院高声喊叫、尖叫毫无意义。
prepared to get in the room to discuss
只有进入会议室，
them. It gets you absolutely nowhere.
才能真正推动问题的解决。
>> Business committee limber.
>> 事务委员会准备就绪。
>> Thank you very much, Mr. Speaker. I want
>> 非常感谢，议长先生。我想
to welcome the prime minister's serious
对首相认真应对严峻权力问题表示欢迎。
engagement with serious power. It is
这对于保障我们的国家安全
essential to safeguarding our national
至关重要。
interest.
利益。
>> Mr. Speaker, the complexities of China
>> 议长先生，中国问题的复杂性
require from Britain a whole of society
需要英国采取全社会的综合应对策略，
approach which is completely impossible
而在政府未能发布明确政策之前，
until the government publishes a clear
这是完全不可能实现的。
China strategy to explain what is
解释中国战略的内容是什么
offlimits and how we're going to
以及哪些领域是禁区，我们将如何
rebalance competition with Chinese
重新平衡与中国工业的竞争，
industry that is six times overs
该工业的补贴规模是我们企业的六倍。现在，
subsidized compared to our firms. Now,
相比我们的企业享有补贴。现在，
last week in Europe, I heard very
上周在欧洲，我清楚地听到我们的合作伙伴表达了
clearly from our partners that they are
他们的担忧，即对中国竞争采取的松懈监管方式
worried that the laxidasical approach to
可能会带来风险，
policing Chinese competition risks
这种风险可能会影响与欧洲的更深层次整合。
deeper integration with Europe. The EU
欧盟方面也有类似的担忧。
has 143 trade measures in place against
针对欧洲已有143项贸易措施生效，
Europe. We have none. So will the prime
而我们则一项也没有。那么，首相是否会
minister now follow through his meetings
兑现他上周的会谈承诺，公布一项
last week and publish a strategy
与我们的盟友协调一致的战略，
coordinated with our allies so we can
以便我们能够…
take out the guesswork and put in place
消除猜测因素，建立起
the guard rails for this important
这段重要关系的保障机制。
relationship.
>> 首相，
>> Prime Minister,
>> 我能否感谢他提出的问题？
>> can I thank him for his uh question?
>> 我能感谢他的提问吗？
Obviously the general approach was set
显然，整体方针已在
out in the uh lady's banquet speech I
女士宴会演讲中阐明，
gave just before Christmas. On the point
该演讲我于圣诞节前夕发表。关于他提到的欧洲问题，
he makes about Europe, this is a really
这是一个非常重要的观点。正如我所提及，
important uh point. Uh as I mentioned,
……
President Mcron went to China just a few
马克龙总统就在几周前访问了中国。
weeks ago. Uh Chancellor Mertz is due to
默克尔总理也即将前往。
go very shortly. Um and he won't be
他不会感到惊讶，
surprised uh to learn that uh the three
因为我们三位作为欧洲三国集团成员，事先进行了讨论，
of us as the E3 discussed in advance uh
……
the approach we would take and we'll
我们将采取的方针，并且我们会
discuss um during the visits and
在访问期间以及
afterwards uh the outcomes and how we go
访问之后讨论成果，以及我们作为欧洲国家集团
forward as a group of European nations.
如何共同推进。
Father of the House Edward Lee.
议会资深议员爱德华·李发言。
>> What absolutely unites everybody in this
>> 在这个议会中，所有人完全一致的是对
place is absolute outrage at the
吉米·赖（Jimmy Lai）所遭受待遇的极度愤慨，
treatment of Jimmy Lie,
>> 他是一名英国公民，唯一的“罪行”就是
>> a British citizen whose only crime is to
为民主而奋斗，并且提出要求
campaign for democracy and to ask the
>> 。。。
Chinese to obey the spirit and the
中国应遵守我们在1997年接管前与他们郑重达成的协议的精神，
letter of the agreement that we made
以及协议的具体条款。
them with them solemnly before the 1997
现在，首相，我在周末看到他表示，
takeover. Now the prime minister I saw
他已经提出了……
the weekend said he'd raised
（后续内容未提供，无法翻译）
respectfully
恭敬地说
with the latest Chinese emperor the case
关于最新的中国领导人问题
of Jimmy Lie respectfully. Doesn't the
以及吉米·李的案子，恭敬地说。难道首相没有意识到
prime minister realize that the Chinese
中国人只认可实力，一切都是如此
only accept strength that everything is
。
a deal? So why didn't he say to them
一项协议？那他为什么不对他们说
there'll be no Chinese embassy until you
在你们停止对我们议会的间谍活动之前，
stop spying us in this house that you
不会有中国大使馆设立，
give an absolute assurance to us on
你们必须就迪亚哥加西亚岛问题向我们作出绝对保证，
Diego Garcia and above all you free
最重要的是，你们必须释放……
Jimmy Lie now.
吉米·李现在。
Mr. Speaker, I raised the case of Jimmy
议长先生，我曾就吉米·李一案向总统提出过，
Li in terms with the president as in
事实上，我确实如此，他也知道，呃，关于二十国集团，
fact I did as he knows uh of the G20
当我第一次会见总统时，
when I met the president for the first
——
uh time and we have updated uh the
呃，时间到了，我们已经向家属通报了
family uh in relation to the progress uh
相关进展情况。嗯，但是对方党派的立场似乎是，
that we've made. Um but the the position
你应该提出吉米·赖的案件，
of the party opposite seems to be uh you
通过……
should raise the case of Jimmy Lie by
（内容未完）
not going to China and raising the case
不前往中国，也不提及吉米·赖案
of Jimmy Lie
吉米·赖案
Committee Tan Singh Desi. Thank you very
谢谢议长先生。我们必须务实地与我们的盟友接触，
much, Mr. Speaker. We must engage
pragmatically with our uh allies and
继续…
with others around the world when it
与世界各国合作，
serves a national interest. And that is
只要这符合国家利益。
why I welcome the prime minister's
因此，我欢迎首相
engagement with both our close ally
与我们亲密的盟友日本的接触，
Japan uh as well as our major trading
以及我们重要的贸易伙伴。
partner China. I also welcome uh my
中国这一合作伙伴。我也欢迎我这位尊敬的右侧议员对
right honorable friend's commitment to
全球战斗机项目的承诺，正如
the global combat air program which as
国防委员会所阐述的那样，该项目具有
the defense committee illustrated is of
至关重要的战略意义，正如我们
vital strategic importance as we uh
所见。
develop the next generation of fighter
研发下一代战斗机。
jets. But our Japanese and Italian
但我们的日本和意大利朋友可以理解地感到紧张，
friends are understandably nervous
因为我们尚未将完整合同正式签署，
because we have as yet not penned uh to
以书面形式确定，正如之前所述。
uh paper the full contract as was
呃...公布完整的合同，就像...
planned last year for Tempest. So can
去年为“风暴”项目所做的规划。那么，
the prime minister clarify when that uh
首相能否澄清该项目的正式合同何时
fully formalized contract on GCAP will
会签署？同时，能否确认
be penned? Uh and uh can he also confirm
时间表和计划是否会
uh that the timeline and program will
……
not be sliding sideways?
不会出现偏离方向的情况吗？
>> Prime Minister,
>> 首相，
>> can I thank him for raising this program
>> 我能否感谢他提出这个项目，
which is a very important program. Uh
这是一个非常重要的项目。呃，
he'll be pleased to know uh I did
他会高兴地知道，呃，我确实……
discuss it in my discussions with the
我在与首相的会谈中讨论了此事，
prime minister uh in Japan and we will
嗯，在日本期间，
be publishing our defense investment
我们将很快公布我们的国防投资计划。
plan uh shortly.
>> 汤姆·查加特。
>> Tom Chugart.
>> 汤姆·图根哈特（Tom Tugendhat）。
>> Yeah.
>> 是的。
>> Thank you, Mr. Speaker. You have been
>> 谢谢您，议长先生。您一直坚定支持我们这些多年前被中华人民共和国制裁的人，
stalwart in standing with those of us
您的立场始终如一，
who were sanctioned by the people's
在那些年里，
republic of China all those years ago
您与我们同舟共济。
and you've been very clear that we stand
您已经非常明确地表示，我们在本院团结一致。
as one in this house. Do you not find it
您难道不像我一样感到惊讶吗，
as surprising as I do that the prime
首相竟然带回了一个协议，
minister has come back with a deal that
该协议取消了对我们六人的制裁，
lifts the sanctions on those six of us
这六人正是我们所关注的对象。
who are still in this house but not the
仍然留在本院的人，但不是
one who isn't nor the lawyers advisers
那些不在此处的人，也不是律师顾问
and academics who support the work of
以及支持本院工作的学者们。
this house. Is this not a direct affront
这难道不是对本院民主的直接侮辱吗？
to the democracy of this place? An
一个…
attempt to divide and conquer that we've
试图分而治之，
seen China play against the European
这是我们看到中国对欧洲议会采取的策略，
Parliament and sadly has tricked our
遗憾的是，这一策略也欺骗了我们的政府。
government too.
>> 首相。
>> Prime Minister.
>> Well, Mr. Speaker, [laughter] I I thank
>> 好的，议长先生，[笑声] 我感谢您提出这一点。
you for raising this point. I know how
我知道这对他本人以及他提到的其他人来说，
much it matters personally uh to him and
是多么重要。嗯，我确实直接提出过这个问题，
to the others that he referenced. Um I
并且那……
did raise it um directly and that uh got
得到了……
the response that restrictions do not
关于限制措施不适用于议员的回应。
apply uh to parliamentarians. I accept
我接受这一挑战，认为我们需要采取行动。
the challenge that we need to go I
我接受这一挑战，
accept the challenge uh the points that
并且同意我们需要做得更进一步。
we need to go further. That doesn't mean
但这并不意味着……
that what we've achieved should be put
我们所取得的成果不应被搁置一旁。
to one side. I accept that we must go
我承认我们必须走得更远，
further and I'll work with uh colleagues
我将与全院各位同事一道努力，
across the house in order to do so. But
以实现这一目标。
in order to go further, we have to
但要走得更远，我们必须……
engage and we have to engage at the
必须进行接触，而且必须在领导人层面进行接触。
leader level.
>> B. 谢谢您，议长先生。嗯，我能否感谢首相对英国与中国交往所采取的成熟态度？
>> B. Thank you, Mr. Speaker. Um, can I
>> 谢谢您，议长先生。嗯，我能否
thank the prime minister on his grownup
感谢首相在英国与中国接触方面
approach to UK engagement with China?
采取的成熟态度？
And can I can I also congratulate him on
我能否也对他就
the agreement for a crackdown on
达成打击小型船舶发动机及零部件制造商的协议表示祝贺，
manufacturers of small boat engines and
这些制造商的行为直接影响到我的
parts which directly impact my
选区？但鉴于该党
constituency? But given that the party
...
opposite wouldn't even have gone to
对方甚至都不会去中国，
China, would you agree with me that the
您是否同意我的观点，即
choice is between a Labor government
选择在于工党政府
doing the hard yards to shut down the
努力关闭走私供应链，还是保守党
smuggler supply chains and the Tory
……
party who prefer posturing and permanent
那些更喜欢做表面文章、在英吉利海峡问题上屡屡失败的政党？
failure in the channel? Hey, Prime
喂，首相，
Minister,
>> 感谢您，
>> thank you for 60% of um of motors uh
有60%的马达，呃，
used across the channel are coming from
用于海峡两岸的马达是来自……
China. So, of course, it's right to
中国。当然，针对中国问题，
engage uh appropriately in China on this
适当地进行接触是正确的，
issue and to get the agreement we got,
并且取得了我们所获得的协议，
Mr. Speaker, on information uh sharing
议长先生，关于信息共享，
and working uh to ensure that those
以及努力确保那些…
engines can't make their way from China
发动机无法从中国运抵
uh to the north coast of France.
法国北海岸。
>> Taylor,
>> 泰勒，
Mr. Speaker, um I'm going to have
议长先生，嗯，我将再有一次机会，再次尝试
another chance, another try at the
——
question my right honorable friend um
我尊敬的朋友在他最初的陈述中提出了问题，
asked in his original statement. Can the
他问首相能否告诉我们，
prime minister tell us what President Xi
习近平主席对吉米·赖案有何评论，
said about the case of Jimmy Lie and
以及是什么让他有信心我们
what gave him the confidence that we
……
might see movement in the case soon? Can
是否很快会看到此案有所进展？
he also let us know what the response
他是否也能告知我们，
was on challenging the bounties put on
对于那些悬赏追捕在英国境内的异见人士的行为，
the heads of uh uh dissident that are
有何回应？
here in the United Kingdom? um and
嗯，以及…
whether he challenged the transnational
他是否对跨国的
repressions that Hong Kongers across the
镇压行动提出质疑，这些镇压是全香港人所担忧的，
country fear and whether there's any
以及是否存在任何可能性，
prospect of them being able to walk the
让他们能够在街头自由行走，
streets without worrying about
而无需担心安全问题。
interference from the Chinese state on
中国国家对我们街头的干涉。
our streets.
>> 首相，
>> Prime Minister,
>> 正如我向议会所述，我提出了关于吉米一案的情况，
>> as I um told the house, I raised the
具体来说
case of Jimmy in terms
关于吉米（黎智英）的案件
details of the discussion. Safe to say
讨论的具体细节。可以肯定地说
um that we've subsequently spoken to
嗯，我们随后已经与
Jim's family uh about that in relation
吉姆的家人就此进行了沟通，
to the wider issues he raises including
涉及他提出的更广泛问题，包括
Hong Kong. Yes, all of those issues were
香港。是的，所有这些问题都已被讨论过。
raised.
已提出。
>> Samantha,
>> 萨曼莎，
>> thank you, Mr. Speaker. I want to thank
>> 谢谢您，议长先生。我想感谢
the prime minister for his incredible
首相在国际舞台上展现出的卓越领导力，
leadership on on an international step
他的领导令人难以置信。
scale which has a direct benefit on us
这一规模对我们具有直接的利益
domestically, not least um the
在国内，尤其是，嗯，
disrupting of the supply chain for um
对小型船只发动机供应链的扰乱。
engines to small boats. I just wonder
我只是想知道，
because it's not a silver bullet to
因为这并非灵丹妙药，无法完全解决问题。
solve the challenge with immigration
解决通过非法途径移民所带来的挑战
through illegal routes whether the
是否曾讨论过TikTok被用作一个平台，
conversation came up about Tik Tok being
用于传播虚假信息和误导性信息，
used as a platform um to to share
以及相关的对话内容，
disinformation and misinformation to
以此影响公众认知。
encourage people to make dangerous
鼓励人们进行危险的旅程。
journeys.
>> 首相，
>> Prime Minister,
>> 我们提出了若干与走私有关的问题，
>> we we we raised a number of issues in
以及……
relation to uh smuggling um uh and um
关于走私，嗯，呃，以及嗯
but the focus was very much on the small
但关注点主要集中在小型
boat uh on the engines for the small
船只上，特别是小型船只的发动机，
boats because of the fact that 60% of
因为其中有60%来自中国。我们必须
them are coming from China. We need to
终止这一供应链，若我们打算
stop that supply chain if we're going to
实现目标的话。
deal with the uh the crossings.
处理这些过境问题。
>> Andrew Mitch.
>> 安德鲁·米奇发言。
>> Thank you, Mr. Speaker. Uh in spite of
>> 谢谢您，议长先生。尽管首相此次归来时所带来的经济成果略显单薄，
the somewhat thin economic gr with which
但他仍然……
he has returned, the prime minister was
（原文未完，无法继续翻译）
absolutely right to visit China. But if
访问中国绝对是正确的决定。但如果
I may return to the issue of human
我可以回到人权问题，特别是关于吉米·赖，
rights and in particular Jimmy Lie, did
首相是否说过，正如全院议员所希望他能说的那样，
the prime minister say, as the whole
……
house would have wished him to say that
this British citizen, nearly 80 years
这位近80岁的英国公民，
old, held in solitary confinement and
被单独监禁，
denied the chance to practice his
并被剥夺了信仰自由的权利，
religion should surely receive clemency
理应获得宽大处理，
and be returned to the United Kingdom or
并被遣返回英国，或者
did he merely deliver a written note?
他只是递交了一份书面说明吗？
>> Minister,
>> 部长，
>> I didn't deliver a written note. I enga
>> 我并非只是递交了一份书面说明。我认真参与了讨论，
I engaged seriously on the issue as he
正如他所期望的那样，
would have expected me to and went into
并深入探讨了相关问题。
the details uh of the case that I was um
关于此案的具体细节，呃，我当时是按照他所期望的方式来陈述的。
making in the way he would have expected
>> 雷切尔，
me to do so.
>> 谢谢议长先生。我的选民，
>> Rachel,
>>
>> thank you Mr. Speaker. My constituent,
the journalist and democracy campaigner
这位记者兼民主运动倡导者
Jimmy Lie was convicted under Hong
吉米·赖因香港严苛的国家安全法下被定罪。
Kong's draconian uh national security
我认真听取了我那位尊敬的右派朋友、首相的发言，
law. I've listened carefully to what my
（此处原文无内容，跳过）
right honorable friend, the prime
minister, has said. We have heard that
部长已经表示。我们已经听说
he has raised this issue uh on his
他在访问期间提出了这个问题。
visit. Uh Jimmy Lie is desperately
吉米·赖目前病情危急，
unwell now. Uh his health is failing.
他的健康状况正在恶化。
I've heard what the prime minister has
我听到了首相的表态，
to say. I'm grateful that the foreign
谢谢发言。我感谢外交大臣将会与吉米的家人会面。
secretary will be speaking to Jimmy's
首相能否向我们说明他的评估，
family. Can the prime minister share
我们是否会在2026年看到吉米·赖获得自由？
with us his assessment of will we see
与我们分享他的评估，我们是否会在
Jimmy Lie free in 2026?
2026年看到黎智英重获自由？
Prime Minister and
首相和
>> I thank her for all the work she does on
>> 我感谢她为她的选民所做的一切工作。
behalf of her uh constituent. Um yes, I
嗯，是的，我确实详细提出了这一点，并且明确表示，
did raise this and in detail and made it
我们正在呼吁对他的
clear um that we were calling for his
…
release uh plus other uh details of the
公开发布有关他健康状况及
situation in which um his health and the
他所处环境的其他相关细节。
situation he's being um held in. Um and
我认为，
um I believe it's the right thing to
在这些问题上，
engage at the highest level on issues of
最高层级的接触是恰当的。
such concern and to have that
对此表示如此关切，并进行那样的对话。
conversation. Um and I believe that is a
嗯，我相信这是一种
far better strategy uh than um putting
远比将头埋进沙子里更好的策略，
your head in your in the sand which is
而这显然是该党所采取的政策。
the policy apparently of the party
显然是该党的政策
officer.
官员。
>> Steven Flynn.
>> 斯蒂文·弗林。
>> Mr. Speaker, as you will be aware when
>> 议长先生，正如您所知，
the prime minister was in China and
当首相访问中国和
Japan, he gave comment that Andrew
日本时，他曾就安德鲁发表了评论。
Mountbatten Windsor should testify
温莎的蒙巴顿应当出庭作证
before Congress in the United States.
在美国国会面前。
What the prime minister chose not to do
首相选择不做的事情是
was to offer an unreserved apology to
向杰弗里·爱泼斯坦的受害者
the victims of Jeffrey Epstein for
给予毫无保留的道歉。
appointing his other friend Peter
任命他的另一位朋友彼得·曼多森
Mandosen as the ambassador to the United
为驻美大使。
States of America. So now that he's back
既然他刚刚从中国和日本回来，
from China in Japan, will he take this
他是否会借此机会采取行动？
opportunity to do just that? And does he
他是否会……
agree with myself that Peter Mandlesen
我同意彼得·曼德尔森
should be subject to a police
应当接受警方调查，
investigation for potential criminality
以查明其在公职期间是否存在潜在犯罪行为。
whilst in public office?
首相，有一份声明。
Prime Minister, there is a statement.
首相，有一项声明。
>> Only SNP uh could uh go about this in
>> 只有苏格兰民族党会以这种方式处理此事，
the way instead of welcoming the hinging
他们没有欢迎对苏格兰威士忌关税的取消，
of tariffs on Scottish whiskey, he
反而提出了一些与中国或日本毫无关系的问题。
raises things that got absolutely
只有…
nothing to do with China or Japan. Only
与中国或日本无关。只是
the S&P have got no interest in at all
标准普尔对此毫无兴趣。
in delivering for Scotland.
他们对为苏格兰争取利益毫无作为。
>> Prime Min, Mr. Speaker, does the prime
>> 首相，议长先生，
minister recall that during the time of
首相是否记得在脱欧谈判期间，
Brexit negotiations that the tries told
谈判方曾表示……
us that we had more to gain outside of
告诉我们，在欧盟之外我们能获得的利益超过在欧盟内部，
the EU than inside and that within days
并且在脱欧后的几天内，
of Brexit we would be signing trade
我们将会与美国和中国签署贸易协议，
deals with the US and China that would
这些协议将会比那些贸易协议更为庞大，
be bigger than the trade deals that
（那些贸易协议）是……
existed with the EU? Now we got what
曾经与欧盟共存？现在我们得到的
what we got was a botch Brexit and
是一场拙劣的脱欧，
isolated from our European neighbors and
使我们与欧洲邻国隔绝，
now they want to extend that isolation
而现在他们想将这种隔绝
to a global scale.
扩展到全球范围。
>> My honorable friend agree with me that
>> 我的尊敬的同僚是否同意我说，
we Britain wouldn't be treated
如果我们英国采取了那样的做法，
decently or or with any any confidence
我们不会被全球邻国或国际友人
by our global neighbors or global
以体面或信任的态度对待，
friends if we'd adopted such an
这样的做法是不可接受的。
approach. Minister,
方法。部长，
>> can I thank you for raising this period
>> 感谢您提及我们历史上的这一时期，
in our history because of course this is
因为这正是2015年至2016年。
2015 2016. The party opposite had a
对方政党在2015年提出了一份宣言，
manifesto in 2015 which dealt with the
其中涉及了……
question of a referendum uh in relation
关于脱欧相关的公投问题。
to Brexit. It also set out their
它还阐明了他们对中国的立场。
position on China. Mr. Speaker, I had a
议长先生，我今天早上看过了，
look at it this morning, 2015, that very
是2015年的那份宣言，
manifesto to strengthen economic links
旨在加强经济联系。
with China, including seeking a free
与中国的关系，包括寻求自由贸易协定。
trade agreement. That used to be their
这曾是他们的立场。
position. And then they veer to the
然后他们又转向了另一边，
other side of the road and now they
现在他们选择视而不见，
stick their head in the sand and pretend
假装不存在问题。
that they can influence events.
他们能够影响事态的发展。
>> William
>> 威廉
seems to be if a bully is big enough,
情况似乎是，如果一个欺凌者足够强大，
rich enough, and powerful enough, the
足够富有，且权势滔天，
pragmatic thing to do is to pay into his
实际的做法就是向他妥协。
protection racket.
敲诈勒索。
Can he at least show some sign of moral
他是否至少能表现出一点道德准则，
compass by accepting the fact that China
承认中国是一个
is a repressive, brutal, communist,
压制性的、残暴的、共产主义的、
totalitarian state which dishonored all
极权国家，玷污了所有…
the provisions of the Hong Kong
香港协议的条款。
agreement.
首相，
Prime Minister,
>> 他们的立场似乎是，如果你有……
>> their position seems to be that if you
如果有人对此表示关切，呃，在……
have I if one has concerns uh in
我是否...如果有人担心...在
relation to China, their position seems
关于中国，他们的立场似乎
to be the pragmatic thing to do is to
是务实的做法，
buy a bag of sand and put your head in
就是买一袋沙子把头埋进去。
it. I don't think that's going to
我认为那不会
influence anything. Nothing said here
产生任何影响。这里没有任何发言。
has any influence if you don't have a
如果没有会面，任何影响力都无从谈起。
meeting.
>> 朱帕。
>> Jupah.
>> 谢谢您，议长先生。我想向我那位尊敬的朋友表示祝贺，
>> Thank you, Mr. Speaker. I want to
>> 谢谢您，议长先生。我想
congratulate my right honorable friend
祝贺我尊敬的朋友
on last week's had some wins including
上周我们取得了一些成果，包括
visas in China. I just wondered if the
在中国的签证问题。我只是想知道
same issue arose in Japan. I did a
日本是否也存在同样的问题。
brilliant visit to the Japan London
前几天我在自己的选区访问了伦敦日本学校，
school in my seat the other day, but
那次访问非常出色，但……
they are finding the dogmatic visa
他们发现保守党政府推行的教条式签证政策
changes made by the conservative
令人感到负担沉重。那么，您是否会对此进行审视，
government burdensome. So will you look
并且赞扬日本所作出的贡献？
into that and also praise the
（原文第4条为不完整句，已合并翻译）
contribution of the Japanese enacted
（原文第5条内容不完整，已合并翻译）
from sushi to bilingual education?
从寿司到双语教育？
Mr. Speaker, we had very productive
议长先生，我们在日本举行了非常富有成效的会谈。
meetings in Japan. Amongst the
讨论内容之一是，
discussions was uh how we open up uh to
如何进一步开放，
more trade between our two economies.
促进我们两国经济之间更多的贸易往来。
>> Richard Tai,
>> 理查德·戴，
>> thank you, Mr. Speaker. The prime
>> 谢谢您，议长先生。首相表示，此次访华有利于英国就业。
minister said that this visit to China
>> 因此，在错误地批准超级
was good for British jobs. So, having
>> （字幕未完，无法继续翻译）
wrongly granted consent to the super
错误地批准了超级
Chinese embassy, can he confirm that it
中国大使馆，他能否确认该建筑将使用
will be built with brilliant British
来自林肯郡的优质英国钢材建造，
steel from Lincolnshire as opposed to
而非中国钢材？
Chinese steel?
正是本届政府采取了…
It was this government that took the
正是本届政府采取了
action on scumthorp to make sure we have
关于斯坎索普的行动，确保我们拥有
British steel at scuntor. One of the
斯坎索普的英国钢铁产业。这是我所做过的
proudest things I've done.
最自豪的事情之一。
>> John Brady.
>> 约翰·布雷迪发言。
>> Thank you, Mr. Speaker. And I welcome
>> 谢谢您，议长先生。我欢迎...
the prime minister's statement facing
首相的声明：正视现实世界。
into the world as it is. Mr. Speaker Dez
议长先生，德兹·布朗，布朗男爵夫人即将退休，
Brown, Baron Brown of Lady is retiring
他将从上议院离任，结束数十年的卓越公共服务，
from the other place after decades of
作为工党成员，
distinguished public service as a Labour
他为国家作出了杰出贡献。
MP for Kumman defense secretary and his
库曼选区议员兼国防大臣及其
work on the prevention of the spread of
在防止核武器扩散方面的工作。
nuclear weapons.
中国是一个重要且不断增长的
China is a significant and growing
核大国，拥有超过600枚核弹头，
nuclear power with over 600 warheads and
拥有超过600枚弹头的核大国，以及
this week the US and Russia new start
本周，美俄《新削减战略武器条约》将届满终止。
treaty comes to an end. Can the prime
首相能否告知我，
minister tell me if the UK is engaging
英国是否正与中国进行最高层级的接触，
with China at the highest levels to
以防范核武器风险，
prevent the risk of nuclear weapons and
并且……
combat nuclear proliferation?
如何遏制核扩散？
>> Prime Minister. Well, can I first start
>> 首相。首先，请允许我向
by paying tribute to uh the contribution
布朗勋爵所作出的贡献表示敬意，
that Lord Brown uh has made a and to
并向他保证，我们的讨论
assure um him that uh our discussions
将继续深入进行。
with China did include how we derisk the
与中国的接触确实包括了如何降低与核武器相关的风险。
situation in relation the risk in
关于这一局势的风险管理。
relation to uh nuclear weapons.
关于核武器的风险。
>> Was it 3:30
>> 是在3点30分吗，
>> when John Major went to Beijing, he
>> 当时约翰·梅杰前往北京， 他…
spoke clearly and said we will not
清晰地发言，并表示我们不会忘记特尔曼广场。
forget Telman Square. In contrast, the
相比之下，首相直到飞机起飞才愿意提及吉米·李的名字。
prime minister refused to say Jimmy
我从未说过我们不应该……
Liy's name himself until he was wheels
（原文此处不完整，无法准确翻译）
up. I have never said we should not
engage with Beijing. I have said we
与北京接触。我曾表示，
should not give them a propaganda visit.
我们不应给予他们一次宣传性质的访问。
And it is extraordinary to abdicate the
而且，放弃对中国共产党责任的担当，
responsibility of the Chinese Communist
这是极不寻常的，
Party whose actions we had to respond to
因为我们必须对其行动作出回应。
and therefore pause trade talks as if
因此暂停贸易谈判，仿佛他们毫无过错。
they have done nothing wrong. Finally,
最后，
the prime minister met with Kai Chi, the
首相会见了凯奇，
man responsible for running two spies
这位负责指挥两名间谍的人，
who are undermining this parliament. He
他们正在破坏本议会的正常运作。他…
excluded that from his statement. Why
他在声明中排除了这一点。为什么
doesn't he tell us why he thought it was
他不告诉我们，为什么他认为与此人会面是可以接受的，
acceptable to meet with this man and
以及他究竟从中获得了什么，
what exactly he got out of it in the
对英国利益有何具体裨益？
British interest?
英国的利益？
>> This is so pathetic.
>> 这真是令人遗憾。
>> We
>> 我们
at the highest level and one to one I
在最高层面进行了一对一的会谈，
raised each of the uh issues of
我提出了我们两国之间的每一个分歧问题，
difference between our two countries
这些分歧问题。
each and every one of them in the way
他们每一个人都以议会所期望的方式行事，
the house would have expected and that
这正是他们所批评的地方。
is what they're criticizing. They they
他们似乎真诚地相信，议长先生，
they seem genuinely to believe, Mr.
这些问题可以被……
Speaker, that these issues can be
（未完待续）
progressed or or or influenced by doing
只有通过行动，才能推动或影响事态发展。
nothing about it. You have to be in the
对此无动于衷是行不通的。
room to have a discussion. That's what
必须亲自参与讨论，才能有所作为。
we did.
这正是我们的做法。
>> Alex,
>> 亚历克斯，
>> thank you, Mr. Speaker. I think it's
>> 谢谢您，议长先生。我认为，
right that the prime minister goes to
如果首相的行为符合所有在此居住者的最佳利益，
China if he's acting in the best
他前往中国是正确的。
interests of all of those that are
去年，双方联合
living here. Last year, the joint
……
committee rights undertook an inquiry on
委员会权利小组对跨国镇压进行了调查。
transnational repression. In front of
在我们面前，有一位来自利兹的年轻香港人，
us, we had Khloe Chung, a young Hong
她名叫钟可儿，
Konger from Leeds who'd been had a 1
曾被悬赏一百万港元，
million Hong Kong dollar bounty put on
以追捕她。
her head. She told us about how she'd
她向我们讲述了她所经历的事情，
been im intimidated, harassed, did the
她曾遭受恐吓和骚扰，
prime minister Speaker, for all the Hong
首相议长，我想为所有在英国的香港人发声，
Kongers in the UK who had bounties on
他们头上悬赏，
their heads, who have been intimidated,
并且一直受到恐吓，
harassed, and ensure that people living
遭受骚扰，并确保居住在英国的人们
in the United Kingdom are safe from the
免受中国政权的威胁。
Chinese regime.
首相。
Prime Minister.
>> 议长先生，正因为如此，我们
>> Mr. Speaker, that's exactly why we
——
raised the issues of human rights at
在访问期间多层面提出了人权问题。
numerous levels on the visit.
>> 莫妮卡。
>> Monica.
>> 谢谢您，议长先生。议长先生，我注意到提及日本时，
>> Thank you, Mr. Speaker. Mr. Speaker, I
[内容未完，无法翻译]
noticed that mention of Japan took the
prime minister one minute and the last
首相，发言时间还有一分钟，这是关于中国
minute of a 10-minute speech on China
和日本的十分钟演讲的最后一分钟。
and Japan. Japan is not only the largest
日本不仅是继欧盟和美国之后，英国最大的外来投资者，
inward investor into the UK apart from
还是一个至关重要的自由主义
the EU and US, but is a vital liberal
国家。
democracy in the Pacific and a key
太平洋地区的民主国家，也是维护地区稳定的重要安全伙伴
security partner in maintaining regional
面对日益增长的中国强势态度，
stability in the face of growing Chinese
鉴于安全风险不断加剧和战略不稳定性增加，
assertiveness given the growing security
在此背景下，
risks and strategic instability across
维护地区安全与稳定显得尤为关键。
the region. Can the prime minister
该地区。首相能否向议会保证，
assure the House that engagement with
与北京的接触不会削弱英国
Beijing will not weaken the UK's
与日本的战略协调，
alignment with Japan, one of our most
日本是我们最重要的民主伙伴之一？
important democratic partners? the prime
首相…
minister.
部长。
>> Yes, I can assure her of that.
>> 是的，我可以向她保证这一点。
>> Jonathan Davis,
>> 乔纳森·戴维斯，
>> thank you very much, Mr. Speaker. Um, in
>> 非常感谢您，议长先生。嗯，关于刚才的声明，呃，接下来
respect of the statement uh following
>>>
the visit to China in Japan, I thank the
关于访问中国和日本，我感谢首相出席会议，
prime minister for being in the room and
并且在场上直面中国，
challenging China on its appalling human
谴责其令人震惊的人权记录，
rights record and also fighting for
同时也为英国就业而奋斗。
British jobs. But in respect of his
但关于他的……
visit to Japan, can I ask did the issue
访问日本期间，我能否请教一下，
of Toyota come up because Toyota is a
是否提到了丰田的问题？因为丰田是
significant employer in Darbisha? It's
达比沙的重要雇主，
worth over 5.5 billion pounds to the
对当地经济贡献超过55亿英镑。
local economy. And can we do more with
我们是否可以在这方面做得更多？
Toyota because it's really good for jobs
丰田因为它对就业非常有利
here?
在这里？
Yes, we did discuss the uh car
是的，我们确实讨论了汽车
manufacturing uh that is going on at the
制造业，目前正在进行的情况。
moment. The potential for further work
以及未来进一步发展的潜力
in that uh regard along with other
在这方面，以及我们两国之间贸易拓展的其他问题上，
issues of trade broadening between our
因此，约翰·威廷，
two countries. So John Witting,
>> 首相将会注意到，大约80%的受制裁的双用途物品
>> the prime minister will be aware that
>> 首相应该知道
some 80% of the sanctioned dual use
约80%受制裁的军民两用
items that Russia is needs for its
俄罗斯制造无人机和导弹所需的物资
drones and missiles that it is firing at
正是这些无人机和导弹每天被用来袭击
civilians and children on a daily basis
平民和儿童。
come from China. He says that he raised
他表示自己曾提出过这一问题。
this. Did he get any assurance that
他是否获得了任何保证，认为…
China will stop supplying Russia?
中国会停止向俄罗斯供货吗？
>> No. quite right to draw attention uh to
>> 不会。确实应当关注这一点，呃，
this and that is precisely why I raised
这正是我再次提出这一问题的原因，呃，
it again uh in terms I won't go into the
关于讨论的细节我就不展开了，
details of the discussion but I did
但我确实提到了。
raise it for the very reason for the
提出这一问题，正是基于他所阐述的理由，
very reasons that he sets out and across
正是基于他所陈述的那些原因，整个议会
this house we're absolutely committed to
坚定致力于实现乌克兰的公正与持久和平，
a just and lasting peace in Ukraine and
这是我们始终关注的重大议题，
this has been an issue of concern for
这一问题一直令我们深切关切。
some considerable period which is why I
一段相当长的时间，这就是我提出这个问题的原因
raised it
我提出了这个问题
>> am Martin
>> 我是马丁
>> Mr. Speaker, I welcome the prime
>> 议长先生，我欢迎首相最近在东京的参与
minister's recent engagement in Tokyo
and the strengthening of our relations
以及加强我们与日本这一重要经济与战略伙伴的关系。
with Japan as a key economic and
他能否解释一下，特别是在海事和国防领域的进口情况，
strategic partner. Can he explain how
例如格里芬海洋公司等方面的具体情况？
import particularly in maritime and
进口，特别是在海事和
defense such as Griffin Marine alongside
防务领域，例如格里芬海事公司（Griffin Marine），以及
the creative industries will benefit
创意产业将受益于
from deeper UK Japan cooperation?
英日更深层次的合作吗？
Because Mr. speaker. Having seen Archie
因为议长先生，看到我的18岁儿子阿奇·科尔，
Cole, my 18-year-old son, a professional
一名目前在东京电视台参赛的职业摔跤手，
wrestler currently competing on Tokyo TV
我深有感触。
in Magic Monday,
在“魔法星期一”议程中，
>> I know firsthand how international
>> 我深知国际交流如何为
engagement can open doors for
个人以及地方企业的港口
individuals and ports of local
开启机遇之门。
businesses alike.
同样的企业。
>> Can I congratulate her son on his uh
>> 我能否对她的儿子取得的成就表示祝贺，呃
achievements uh and in relation tomemes
以及在社交媒体和企业方面的表现？
and businesses? Yes, we discuss how we
是的，我们讨论了如何
can enhance um our engagement and
加强我们的合作，
enhance growth and jobs uh right across
促进各领域的增长和就业。
all of our constituencies including
我们所有的选区，包括她的选区。
hers.
>> 您发言。
>> You take
>> 麦克比先生。
>> Mr. McB.
>> 谢谢您，先生。
>> Thank you, Mr.
>> 谢谢您，...先生。
>> Speaker. Yeah.
>> 议长。是的。
>> Does the prime minister accept that in
>> 首相是否承认，
his rush to hoover up economic crumbs
在急于从习近平主席那里攫取经济利益的过程中，
from President Xi due to his appalling
由于他对我国经济的糟糕处理，
handling of our economy, he is having to
他不得不……
increase strategic dependence on
加剧对北京的战略依赖。
Beijing. Mhm.
嗯。
>> The public see the risks he's taking
>> 公众看到了他对英国安全所冒的风险。难道他看不到吗？
with UK security. Does he?
>> 是的。
>> Yeah.
>> Prime Minister,
>> 首相，
>> Mr. Speaker, the first thing I'd say is
>> 议长先生，我首先要说的是，
they crash the economy. So, lectures
他们搞垮了经济。因此，
from them uh on the economy are not
对方关于经济的教训
welcome. As I said in my statement,
并不受欢迎。正如我在声明中所说，
national security is at the heart of our
国家安全是我们对华政策的核心，
approach to China as it is to every
这同样适用于我们所关注的每一个议题。
issue that we take up. uh and it is
嗯，我们完全可以就可供我们利用的机遇展开讨论，
quite possible to have a discussion
同时也能就相关挑战进行深入探讨。
about the opportunities available to our
——（此处英文字幕不完整，无法继续翻译）
country whilst also safeguarding our
在保障我们国家安全的同时，也保护我们的国家利益。
national security. That's what we're
这就是我们以成熟稳重的方式所做的工作。
doing in a grown-up mature way.
>> 非常感谢您，议长先生。
>> Thank you very much, Mr. Speaker.
针对我右侧同僚提出的问题，
Further to the question from my right
（后续内容未提供，无法翻译）
honorable friend from Birmingham Hodge
来自伯明翰霍奇的尊敬的议员朋友
Hill and Sleyhole North, the
以及希尔和斯莱霍尔北选区的议员，
anti-dumping measures that we impose on
我们对进入本国的中国产品实施的反倾销措施，
Chinese goods into this country protect
保护了斯托克-特伦特数百个就业岗位。
hundreds of jobs in Stoke on Trent.
斯托克（Stoke-on-Trent）的数百个就业岗位。
Whether that be in the ceramic table
无论是在陶瓷餐具制造行业，
wear manufacturing sector or the
还是在米切尔工厂的轮胎翻新部门，
retreading tires at the Mitchell
首相是否能够保证，
factory. Is the prime minister able to
在经济工作方面，
give a guarantee that as economic work
……
with China continues that these measures
与中国的关系持续发展，这些措施
will not be junked because it's not an
不会被废弃，因为这不是一项
abstract measure, Mr. Speaker, it is
抽象的措施，议长先生，
protecting hundreds of jobs in a part of
它是在保护该国最需要就业的地区的数百个岗位。
the country that most needs them.
最需要这些岗位的地区。
>> I thank you for raising uh this issue.
>> 感谢您提出这个问题。
Um and I can give him that assurance. I
嗯，我可以向他保证这一点。
know how much it matters and that's the
我知道这件事的重要性，这也是我们采取的方针。
approach that we've taken.
>> 克里斯，议长先生，过去……
>> Chris, Mr. Mr. Speaker, over the past
>> 克里斯，议长先生，在过去
weeks, thousands of Chinese fishing
数周以来，数千艘中国渔船被困，
boats have been trapped, creating up to
在东海形成了长达
a 300 mile long blockage in the East
约300英里的封锁带，
China Sea of Japan, seen by many as a
这一局面被许多人视为对日本的
strategy for future blockade. Given a
未来封锁战略。鉴于此，
huge reliance in these roots for trade,
对这些贸易根基的高度依赖，
this actually will cause global economic
实际上将引发全球经济震荡，
shock threatening thousands of jobs in
威胁苏格兰数以千计的就业岗位，
Scotland and dramatically increased cost
并大幅推高生活成本。
of living. So, can the prime minister
那么，首相能否……
tell the house what explanation has
向议会说明中方对此行为所作的解释
Chinese counterparts gave for this
以及中方对此行为的说明内容
behavior and what subsequent discussions
以及他与日本首相就维护海上安全所进行的后续讨论
he had with Japanese prime minister
他与日本首相就维护海上安全进行的讨论情况
about maintaining maritime security in
有关维护海上安全的具体内容
the region? This issue was raised both
该地区？这一问题在中国和日本均被提出，
in China and in Japan um because it is
因为这显然是一个令人关切的问题，
obviously a cause of um concern and
以及地区不稳定因素，
regional instability matters not just in
不仅影响该地区，
the region but globally as well and
也对全球产生影响。
therefore I did discuss it both in China
因此，我确实在中国和
and in Japan.
日本都进行了讨论。
>> Janet Dy.
>> 珍妮特·戴。
>> Thank you madame deputy speaker. I thank
>> 感谢议长女士。我感谢首相的声明，但
the prime minister for his statement but
——
can you tell the house what steps the
请问政府正在采取哪些措施
government is taking to protect
以保护议员及其他公共领域人士
parliamentarians and others in public
免受外国势力的影响？
life from foreign influence?
首相，请回答。
Prime Minister.
首相。
>> Mr. Speaker, there's a number of
>> 议长先生，有若干措施
measures u Madame Deputy Speaker, my
尊敬的副议长女士，请允许我更正，我们采取了若干措施，
apologies, a number of measures that
包括……
we've taken, including um the further
进一步赋予我们的权力和工具，
powers and tools that we've given to our
以便我们……
security and intelligence uh services.
安全与情报部门。
>> David Mundal.
>> 大卫·蒙达尔发言。
>> Thank you, Madam Speaker. Can I echo the
>> 谢谢您，议长女士。我想表达对吉姆·华莱士的敬意。
tributes to Jim Wallace? He was one of
>> 他是苏格兰最重要的政治人物之一，
the most significant Scottish
>> 具有深远影响。
politicians of his generation, and it
他是他那一代的政治家，
was a privilege both to know him and to
能够认识他并与他共事，是一种荣幸。
work with him. I think, Madame Deputy
我认为，议长女士，
Speaker, we've established that the
我们已经确认首相当时就在场。
prime minister was in the room. But what
但是，什么...
difference will it make? What difference
这会带来什么不同？
will it make for people who weren't in
对于那些不在乌克兰现场的人来说，
the room in Ukraine?
会有什么不同？
>> A huge difference. So that's why I
>> 巨大的不同。这就是为什么我
discussed it with Vladimir Zilinski
要与弗拉基米尔·泽连斯基讨论此事。
before I went in terms and that's why
在我进入任期之前，因此
I'll discuss it with him again in coming
我将在未来几天再次与他讨论此事。
days in terms.
关于任期的问题。
>> Alex Baker.
>> 亚历克斯·贝克。
>> Thank you, Madame Deputy Speaker. I want
>> 谢谢您，副议长女士。我想…
to welcome the prime minister's
欢迎首相此次出访的领导力，
leadership on this trip, including his
包括他在日本关于全球紧凑型空中项目价值的讲话。
words in Japan about the value of the
这不仅是一个战略上重要的项目，
global compact air program. This is not
也是一个具有深远意义的计划。
only a strategically important program
（原文第5条为句子未完，结合上下文翻译）
for global security and autonomy, but
对全球安全与自主权至关重要，但
important for businesses uh grown out of
对于我选区内发展起来的企业也同样重要，
my constituency including BAEA systems
包括BAEA系统和Kinetic公司。
and kinetic. CAN THE PRIME MINISTER
首相能否强调他正在开展的工作，
HIGHLIGHT the work he is doing to ensure
以确保……
this critical endeavor makes progress?
这一关键努力取得进展了吗？
Look, can I thank you for that u
请允许我感谢您提出这个问题，
question because um Japan is a key um uh
因为日本是一个关键的，
colleague partner when it comes to
在防务和安全方面的重要合作伙伴，
defense and um security and that's why
这也是为什么——
across a range of issues u we discussed
我们讨论了多个议题
what more we can do including on GCAP
包括我们在全球气候行动伙伴关系（GCAP）方面还能做些什么
>> Martin Vickers. Uh thank you, Madam
>> 马丁·维克斯。谢谢您，女士副议长。
Deputy Speaker. In in uh reference to an
关于之前的一个问题，首相……
earlier question, the uh prime minister
（内容未完，需后续字幕补充）
mentioned Skunkthorp Steelworks where
提到了斯坎克索普钢铁厂，
hundreds of my constituents are
数百名我的选民在那里工作。
employed. Uh we welcome the government's
呃，我们欢迎政府迄今为止的支持。
support to date. Was he able to discuss
他是否能够讨论一下，
uh the ownership Jingier's ownership uh
呃，京杰尔的所有权问题，呃？
with the his Chinese [clears throat]
与他的中国同行——【清嗓子】
opposite number? Is he able to give any
他是否能够向我的选民提供任何
positive assurances to my constituents
关于他们长期未来的积极保证？
about their long-term future? Yeah,
是的，
Prime Minister,
首相，
>> can I um give this assurance to his uh
>> 我能否向他的选民保证，
constituents that uh we absolutely
我们绝对相信钢铁在本国制造的重要性，
believe in the importance of steel being
这正是我们采取相关措施的原因，
made in this country and that is why we
正如他所知，
took the measures as he knows on a
我们采取了这些措施。
Saturday uh to take the steps that were
星期六，呃，采取了必要措施，
necessary in relation to steel
以应对其选区内的钢铁生产问题。
production in his constituency.
>> 亚历克斯·鲍林格发言。
>> Alex Ballinger.
>> 谢谢您，副议长女士。嗯，
>> Thank you, Madam Deputy Speaker. Um, the
……
prime minister will know there are many
首相将会知道，
excellent West Midlands businesses that
西米德兰兹地区有许多优秀企业，
export to China, including great car
它们向中国出口产品，
makers like JLR, the Morgan Motor
包括像捷豹路虎、摩根汽车公司和阿斯顿·马丁这样杰出的汽车制造商，
Company, and Aston Martin, collectively
这些企业合计起来…
worth the most of any region in the UK,
英国所有地区中价值最高的，
I will say. Um, can the, uh, prime
我想说。嗯，首相能否阐述一下，
minister outline how his, um, trip to
他此次访华行程，
China, including the 30-day visa-free
包括30天免签证入境政策，
travel, will benefit these businesses
将如何惠及这些企业？
and drive jobs and exports in our
并推动我们地区的就业和出口？
region? prime minister.
首相。
>> Well, he'll be pleased to know that uh
>> 他会很高兴知道，呃，捷豹路虎随同我们一同出访，
JLR were there with us on the delegation
呃，在中国的代表团中，
uh in China and they're very acutely
他们对此非常敏锐，
aware of the difference uh the better
了解与中国之间更优贸易和经济措施所带来的差异，
trade and economic measures with China
以及这些措施对他们的商业活动
will have in relation to their business
和其选区内就业的影响。
and jobs in his constituency.
>> 理查德·F.
>> Richard F.
>> 理查德·F。
>> Thank you, Madam Deputy Speaker. In
>> 谢谢您，副议长女士。
2023, the Intelligence and Security
2023年，情报与安全委员会报告指出，
Committee reported that quote, "The UK's
引述原文：“英国的学术机构为中国提供了
academic institutions provide a rich
丰富的土壤，
feeding ground for China to achieve both
以实现其双重目标。
political influence and economic
政治影响力与经济利益。
advantage. Can the Prime Minister let us
首相能否告知我们，
know was the issue of interference in
关于干预英国大学的问题，
the UK universities raised with
是否曾向习近平主席提出？
President Xi?"
习主席吗？”
>> Minister,
>> 部长，
>> I raised a wide range of uh issues of
>> 我向议会提出了广泛的关切问题，
concern to this house uh with President
>> 也向纪总统表达了这些关切，正如他所预料的那样。
Gi as he would have expected.
>>
>> Rachel Taylor.
>> 雷切尔·泰勒。
>> Thank you, Madam Deputy Speaker. Growing
>> 感谢副议长女士。
our relationship with China could boost
加强我们与中国的关系，可能促进
our motor manufacturing industry. The
我们汽车制造业的发展。
prime minister will know only too well
首相对此定然深有体会，
that small businesses in this sector are
因为该行业中的小型企业正面临着…
the engine of economic growth in my
我选区乃至整个西米德兰兹地区经济增长的引擎。
constituency and right across the West
他能否阐述此次访问将如何帮助北沃里克郡和贝德沃斯的小型企业？
Midlands. Can he set out how his visit
中部地区。他能否说明他的访问
will help small businesses in North
将如何帮助北
Warshire and Bedworth?
沃里克郡和贝德沃思（North Warwickshire and Bedworth）的小企业？
>> Prime Minister.
>> 首相发言。
>> Well, um Mr. Speaker, by by and thank
>> 嗯，议长先生，感谢您的提问。
you for a question. This is so important
>> 这非常重要，
in terms of the opportunities uh that we
>> 因为这关系到我们所拥有的机遇，
have and that's why we had
>> 这也是为什么我们……
representatives from motor manufacturing
来自汽车制造业的代表
with us. They're only too well aware of
与我们同在。他们非常清楚
the great advantages uh that taking uh a
充分利用这些机会所带来的巨大优势，
full benefit of the opportunities will
这将
have for her constituents and others.
对她的选民及其他人产生的重要影响。
>> Dr. Andrew Mary,
>> 安德鲁·玛丽博士，
>> Prime Minister's friend, Baroness Helena
>> 首相的朋友，赫勒娜·肯尼迪女男爵，
Kennedy, a sanctioned person, clearly
一位被制裁人士，显然
believes that the juice wasn't worth the
认为所付出的努力得不偿失，
squeeze or indeed the price of the plane
甚至不值那架飞机的价格。
tickets because she's described the
因为她形容
returns the prime minister has secured
首相所取得的回报
as meager. She's right, isn't she?
微不足道。她说得对，不是吗？
>> Prime Minister,
>> 首相，
>> I've known Helena for many, many years.
>> 我认识海伦娜很多年了。
We shared a room when we worked together
我们曾在同一办公室共事。
in chambers. We agree on many, many
我们在许多事情上意见一致，
things, but not everything.
但并非全部。
Alex Boris Curtis.
亚历克斯·鲍里斯·柯蒂斯。
>> Thank you, Madame Deputy Speaker. I
>> 谢谢您，副议长女士。我…
thank the prime minister for his
感谢首相的声明，以及他关于
statement and for what he said about
呼吁中国停止支持俄罗斯非法战争行动的发言。我们不能
calling on China to end support for
忽视对我们海岸构成的威胁，
Russia's illegal war effort. We cannot
…
ignore the threat to our shores that
comes from them. As we know very well in
这来自他们。正如我们在
Wales where Nathan Gil, the Reform UK,
威尔士非常清楚的那样，内森·吉尔，改革英国党前威尔士领导人，
former leader in Wales, serving 10 and a
因接受俄罗斯贿赂，
half years in prison for taking bribes
被判处十年半监禁。
from Russia. So will the prime minister
那么，首相是否会……
again join me in condemning that
请大家再次与我一道谴责那种背信弃义的行为，
treacherous activity and reassure me
并向我保证，
that he will continue to push China on
他将继续就这一重要问题向中国施压，
this important point?
是吗？
>> Yes, I will. And I'm I'm grateful for
>> 是的，我会的。对此我深表感谢，
raising the shocking case of Nathan Gil
提出内森·吉尔令人震惊的案件
as he rightly says I think 10 and a half
正如他所言，我认为十年半的刑期
years for taking bribes in relation to
是因涉及俄罗斯和改革领导人的受贿案件
Russia and the leader of reform is not
竟然连引起关注的兴趣都没有，
even interest enough to make an
甚至不足以引发一次讨论。
investigation to see whether that's the
调查以确定这是否是
extent which it won't be of Russian
俄罗斯影响其党派的程度。
influence in his party.
>> 林肯议员 谢谢您，副议长女士。感谢首相
>> Lincoln J Thank you, Madame Deputy
的发言。
Speaker. I thank the prime minister for
议长先生。我感谢首相
his statement. I just want clarification
关于他的声明，我只是想澄清一下
on uh the members of this house who were
本院中哪些议员曾被正式制裁。
formally sanctioned. The prime minister
首相说，
said, "President Xi told me that all
“习近平主席告诉我，所有议员
parliamentarians are now free to travel
现在都可以自由出行。”
to China. Does that mean that they are
对中国。这是否意味着他们不再受到法律制裁，
no longer legally sanctioned and did he
他是否获得了书面确认？
get that in writing?"
>> 首相，
>> Prime Minister,
>> 就此事，我的理解是，
>> that is my understanding in relation to
>> 据我了解，关于
all parliamentarians.
各位议员。
Um what
嗯，什么
>> what I in relation to parliamentarians
>> 关于议员，我的看法是
um I accept that in relation to others
嗯，对于其他人，我是认可的
um we do need to um see how much further
嗯，我们确实需要看看还能走多远
we can go.
我们可以开始了。
>> Matt Bishop.
>> 马特·毕晓普发言。
>> Thank you Madame Deputy Speaker. I thank
>> 感谢副议长女士。我感谢首相的声明。
the prime minister for his statement. I
我想知道他是否同意我的看法，认为……
wondered if he agrees with me that the
（原文未完，无法继续翻译）
security of this country is the
本国安全始终是
government's first and foremost priority
政府的首要且最重要的任务。
at all times.
一直如此。
>> Prime Minister.
>> 首相发言。
>> Yes, I do. It's front and center of
>> 是的，我确实如此认为。这是我们工作的核心和重中之重。
everything we do. um wherever we're
我们所做的一切。嗯，无论我们身处何地，
acting on the world stage.
在国际舞台上采取行动。
>> Ben object.
>> 本议员反对。
>> Thank you very much speaker. Um I just
>> 非常感谢议长。嗯，我只是想就相关问题继续追问，
wanted to follow up on the questions
...
from the chair of the defense select
来自国防委员会主席和GCAP成员的发言。
committee and the member forot on GCAP.
嗯，我们知道下一轮GCAP的资金即将耗尽，
Um we know that the funding for the next
仅剩几个月时间，
round of of GCAP is shortly going to run
对于Edgewing项目来说，
out in a matter of months for Edgewing
资金即将用尽。
and for the uh British phase of the
关于该项目的英国阶段，
program. Um it's been reported that this
据报道，由于国防投资计划的推迟，
is being delayed due to the delay to the
该阶段的进展也因此被延迟。
defense investment plan. Will the
请问，下一阶段GCAP的合同是否会
contract for the next phase of GCAP be
按计划签订？
signed before the defense investment
在防务投资计划公布之前签署的？
plan is published?
防务投资计划何时公布？
>> He'll be pleased to know this was a
>> 他会很高兴知道，这在日本是一个讨论的话题。
matter of discussion in um Japan. Um and
嗯，防务投资计划将会……
the defense investment plan will be
（内容未完，无法翻译）
published very soon.
很快将会发布。
>> Calvin Bailey.
>> 卡尔文·贝利。
>> Thank you, Madam Deputy Speaker. Mark
>> 感谢议长副手女士。马克
Carney rightly challenged fellow middle
卡尼正确地敦促其他中等强国停止自欺欺人，
powers to stop living a lie and
并且...
recognize the changes in the
认识到地缘政治格局的变化，
geopolitical landscape because
因为关于国际秩序的既定假设已不再成立。
comfortable assumptions about the
我们曾经习以为常的假设，
international order are no longer true.
现已不再真实。
The system which once we benefited from
曾经令我们受益的体系，
cannot become the source of our
不能成为我们屈从的根源。
subordination. It was therefore
因此，
important to hear the prime minister's
听到首相对日本GCAP的坚定承诺非常重要。
firm commitment to GCAP in Japan. And
他是否同意我的看法，即对……的投资
does he agree with me that investment in
（后文未完，无法翻译完整）
programs like GCAP is essential to
像GCAP这样的项目对于
address this ge geopolitical challenge?
应对这一地缘政治挑战至关重要。
>> Yeah,
>> 是的，
>> minister.
>> 部长阁下。
>> Well, uh yes, I do. And he's right to
>> 嗯，是的，我同意。他说得没错，
emphasize the changes in the
强调地缘政治格局的变化，
geopolitical uh landscape and that's why
这也是我们为何相应调整了与
we've approached our relationship to the
美国、欧洲、印度和中国的关系。
US uh to Europe, to India and China
美国、欧洲、印度和中国
accordingly.
相应地。
>> Greg Smith.
>> 格雷格·史密斯。
>> Thank you, Madame Deputy Speaker. In his
>> 谢谢您，副议长女士。在他关于首相所称的“分歧领域”的讨论中，
discussions on what the prime minister
首相在这些讨论中，
somewhat mildly describes as areas of
他对这些分歧的描述相当温和，
difference, did he raise the discovery
他是否提及了这一发现？
of kill switches and hidden comms
关于中国制造的太阳能板中是否存在断电开关和隐蔽通讯装置，
devices in Chinese manufactured solar
如果存在，他是否已经采取了行动？
panels? And if he did, can he assure us
如果采取了，他能否向我们保证，
that rather than politely asking for
他不是仅仅礼貌地要求停止这种做法，
this practice to stop, he demanded it?
而是坚决地提出了要求？
here.
在这里。
>> Madame Deputy Speaker, we raised all of
>> 女副议长，我们提出了所有敏感的问题，
the sensitive um issues and we did it um
并且是直接了当地提出的，
in direct terms and in the room and that
当面提出的，
to my mind is the right way of uh trying
在我看来，这才是正确的处理方式。
to make progress on these very important
就这些非常重要的问题取得进展。
issues. Richard Baker.
理查德·贝克。
>> Madame Deputy Speaker, it was a
>> 女副议长，能够与吉姆·华莱士在好莱坞共事，是我的荣幸，
privilege to serve with Jim Wallace in
我愿意表示赞同，
Hollywood and can I associate myself
……
with the tribute to him following trade
对他的致敬随后是关于贸易的内容
deals with Europe, China and India worth
与欧洲、中国和印度达成的贸易协议，价值数亿英镑，
hundreds of millions of pounds for
为苏格兰企业带来收益，
Scottish businesses and defense
以及国防合同，
contracts securing thousands of jobs.
保障了数千个就业岗位。
Can the prime minister tell us how he
首相能否告诉我们他将如何
will build on this success of Scotland?
在苏格兰取得的成功基础上继续努力？
And does he agree it's about time that a
他是否同意，现在是时候让苏格兰政府
Scottish government with the same level
对苏格兰企业展现同等的雄心壮志了？
of ambition for Scottish businesses?
对苏格兰企业的雄心？
Well, it it's astonishing that the S&P
令人震惊的是，标准普尔
are simply not interested in the
对我们在印度贸易协议上取得的进展
progress we've made in the India trade
完全不感兴趣，
deal, which is hugely beneficial to
而这项协议对苏格兰企业极为有利。
Scottish businesses. Um, and in relation
关于这一点，
uh to the h havinging of tariffs that
嗯，关于今天生效的针对中国的关税措施，
comes into effect today in relation to
以及苏格兰企业对此的影响，
China and the businesses in Scotland
他们完全清楚这对他们意味着什么，
know exactly what it means to them,
这也是他们为何感到庆幸的原因。
which is why they're celebrating. The
（原文未完，无法翻译）
S&P can't bring themselves to even
标准普尔甚至无法接受这一点。
welcome it.
>> 吉姆·阿利斯特，
>> Jim Alistister,
议长先生，我确实承认
Mr. Mr. Speaker, I certainly acknowledge
关于关税缓解措施，
the tariff easement in respect of
……
Scottish whiskey and it's apparent uh
苏格兰威士忌，显然，呃，
the apparently superior Bush Mills
我选区的布什米尔斯威士忌显得更为优质。
whiskey from my constituency.
但是，我能否请教首相，
But but could I ask the prime minister
他的访问是否会对……
whether his visit will do anything to
（内容未完）
address the proliferation of heavily
解决大量
subsidized Chinese vehicles which are
中国政府高度补贴的车辆泛滥问题，
flooding our nation particularly in the
这些车辆尤其在我国市场大量涌入，
bus sector where recently we now have
尤其是在公交领域，最近我们已经拥有了
500 subsidized Chinese vehicles courtesy
500辆由中国政府补贴的车辆，感谢于此。
of transport for London on the streets
伦敦街头的交通运输问题
of our capital city. Whereas in both
在我们的首都街道上。而在
Scotland and in my constituency, we
苏格兰和我的选区，我们
build the highest quality of buses. Will
制造最高品质的公交车。请问
there be any action to support British
是否会采取任何措施支持英国制造业？
buses as a result of what the prime
由于首相所寻求采取的措施，公交车服务受到影响吗？
minister is seeking to do?
>> 首相，
>> Prime Minister,
>> 我看到我们已经开启了一场威士忌竞赛。嗯，但他说得很对。
>> I see we've opened a whiskey
>> 我看我们开启了一场威士忌
competition. Um but he he's quite right.
竞赛。嗯，但他说的很对。
It is really important that uh we
非常重要的是，呃，我们
champion the building of buses and so
要大力支持在英国制造公交车以及其他许多产品，
much else uh in the United Kingdom where
因为我们在这方面有许多优秀的典范，
we got great examples of that and that's
这正是为什么我们始终坚持将国家利益放在首位的原因。
why we will always put the national
——（后文未完）
interest first.
利益至上。
>> Kevin Bonavir.
>> 凯文·博纳维尔。
>> Thank you madam deputy speaker and I
>> 感谢副议长女士，我
welcome the prime minister's report back
欢迎首相就其访华和访日行程所做的报告。
from his visits to China and Japan
从他对中国和日本的访问中
something that the previous Tory
这是之前保守党政府多年拒绝做的事情。
governments refused to do for many
他……我发现许多讨论的问题，
years. He ra he I found many of the
包括人权、贸易、
issues discussed human rights uh trade
安全等。
security. Uh I'm particularly interested
我尤其感兴趣的是……
in what he had to say about the border
关于他所谈及的边境安全方案，
security pack because my position
因为我的立场是，
Stevens are very concerned about the
斯蒂文斯先生对小艇危机深感担忧。我们已经与法国达成了
small boats crisis. We've already had
国际协议，
international agreements with France and
并且…
Germany. This is a new one with China.
德国。这是与中国的新合作项目。
I'd like to know more about how this is
我想了解更多关于这项工作的具体情况。
going to work. How can I do that?
我该如何了解？
Well, can I He's right to put this
好的，我可以——他将这套方案作为一个整体来提出是正确的，
package as one because what we're doing
因为我们正在做的事情是……
on small boats is uh with China is
关于小型船只的问题，呃，与中国相关的是
looking at the source of the engines
正在调查发动机本身的来源。
themselves. What we're doing with
我们与德国合作的工作是，嗯，
Germany is the transport um of these
通过欧洲运输这些零部件。我们正在做的事情是
parts through Europe. What we're doing
...
in France uh is working with the French
在法国，呃，我们正在与法国方面合作，
to tackle the crossings themselves.
共同应对非法越境问题。
>> Dr. Kieran Mullen,
>> 基兰·穆伦博士，
>> Madame Deputy Speaker, the whole house
>> 女副议长，整个议会都能亲眼目睹，
can see with their own eyes what's
发生的情况是…
happening here. Prime Minister on PayPal
这里正在发生的事情。首相在PayPal上的行动
has the support of more than 400 MPs
得到了400多名议员的支持
that they want to show the support of
他们希望表达支持的意愿
someone can fill every single seat on
有人能够填满对面所有的议席
the opposite side and down to double
并且人数减少到一半
doors. And we all drift away as the
门扉。而随着陈述的推进，我们都逐渐走神。
statement progresses. But even at the
但即便是在陈述的开头，
start of this statement, at the start of
在这份陈述的开端，
this statement, the prime minister
首相甚至没有权威去
didn't even have the authority to
...
command two or three benches of MPs
指挥着两三排议员席位支持他。
behind him. He's clearly on his way out.
他显然已经走到了尽头。
But the problem is in his desperation to
但问题在于，他为了拼命维护自己的立场，
show up his position, he's trading away
正在出卖我们的国家利益。
our national interest. Can he name can
他能说出……吗？
he name a single tangible benefit he
他能说出他在保障香港市民权利方面取得的任何实质性成果吗？
secured in terms of the rights of Hong
>> 首相提问时间。
Kongers?
>> 是的，我们提出了香港问题。
>> Prime Minister question.
>> 首相提问时间。
>> Yes, we raised the issues of Hong Kong.
>> 是的，我们提出了香港问题。
We raised the issues. I I find it
我们提出了这些问题。我感到
astonishing that their position is that
令人震惊的是，他们的立场竟然是
they want all these issues. They say
他们希望所有这些问题都存在。他们声称
they take these issues seriously. They
他们对这些问题非常重视。他们
say of great concern. They stay here
表示极为关切。他们留在这里
notwithstanding no one else is listening
尽管没有其他人在听，
and raise them on the benches greatly.
他们仍在议席上大声提出这些问题。
And then they say it's so important to
然后他们说这对我来说非常重要。
me. The one thing I don't want you to do
我唯一不希望你做的，
is to go to China and have a discussion
就是去中国进行讨论。
about them at the highest level. It's a
关于他们的最高层面事务。
pathetic approach, unserious approach to
这是一种可悲的、缺乏严肃性的外交政策态度。
foreign policy.
>> 雅各布·科利尔发言。
>> Jacob Collier.
>> 感谢您，副议长女士。
>> Thank you, Madam Deputy Speaker. The
>> 谢谢您，副议长女士。
prime minister may have seen that the
首相可能已经注意到，
Japanese ambassador to the UK, Hiroshi
日本驻英国大使铃木浩史，
Suzuki, was recently in Manchester
最近在曼彻斯特，
trying Boditan's bitter. The prime
试饮博迪坦的苦味酒。首相
minister will know the importance of
会明白这一点的重要性。
brewing to my constituency and perhaps
正酝酿着送往我的选区，也许
in celebration of these trade deals. He
是为了庆祝这些贸易协议。
would like to encourage the ambassador
他希望鼓励大使
to come and sample some of the best beer
来品尝一些最好的啤酒，
in the brewing capital of Burton on
来自酿酒之都伯顿。
trend.
趋势。
>> Prime Minister.
>> 首相。
>> Yes, we certainly should uh encourage
>> 是的，我们确实应该鼓励这一点，
that and I'll take the first opportunity
我将抓住第一个机会
to do so
来这样做。
>> Graeme Leader.
>> 格雷姆·利德先生。
>> Thank you, Madame Deputy Speaker. Um I'm
>> 感谢您，副议长女士。嗯，
glad that the prime minister enjoys the
我很高兴首相和我一样喜欢这场辩论的激烈气氛，
drama as much as I do and for the record
作为记录，我确实对印度贸易协议表示欢迎，
I did welcome the Indian trade deal very
非常欢迎。
publicly. So um you know I perhaps he
公开地。所以，嗯，你知道，我想他
may wish to correct the record in that.
也许希望对此更正记录。
I'd like to focus however on a really
然而，我想重点关注一个对我自己选区就业非常重要的问题，
significant issue for employment in my
那就是奥尔德……呃，
own constituency which is the alder uh
（内容未完，需补充后续字幕以完成翻译）
site part of the the green free port in
作为绿色自由港的一部分
which have expressed a significant
已经表达了重大投资兴趣。
investment interest in. I fully
我完全理解
understand the national security
需要解决的国家安全问题，
concerns that need to be addressed in
并且对此深表关注。
this but a decision is long overdue in
这一决定早该做出了，
this. It's been with the government for
但政府对此拖延已久。
a long long time. There is investor
投资者对此感到不安，
jitteriness about it. Supply chain is uh
供应链也因此困扰，
is vexed about it and it's certainly not
这显然不是理想的状态。
helping the just transition and putting
帮助实现公正转型，同时
putting significant job opportunities at
也将大量就业机会置于风险之中。
risk. When will the decision be taken
何时才能做出决定，
and either let them get on with it or
要么让他们继续推进，
move on to another opportunity? I
要么转而抓住其他机遇？我…
>> prime minister,
>> 首相，
>> can I thank him for raising this issue
>> 我感谢他提出这一问题，
which is a concern to his constituents
这是他选民关心的问题，
and and across Scotland and indeed the
也是整个苏格兰乃至整个英国的关切。
United Kingdom. Um, no decision has yet
嗯，目前尚未作出任何决定，
been made and I'll update the house as
已经取得进展，我会尽快向议会通报最新情况。
soon as I can.
>> 乔什·迪恩发言。
>> Josh Dean.
>> 感谢副议长女士，我感谢首相的……
>> Thank you, Madam Deputy Speaker, and I
>> 谢谢您，副议长女士，我
thank the prime minister for his
感谢首相的
statement today. Last Thursday I held a
今天的声明。上周四，我在毕晓普斯特福德举行了一场
public meeting with the Hong Kong
与香港社区的公开会议。我们聚集一堂，
community in Bishop Stford. We met to
讨论拟议中的无限期居留权变更，
discuss the proposed changes to
但在此过程中，
indefinite leave to remain, but there
……
was real strength of feeling about the
对于吉米·赖案以及香港的民主自由，确实存在强烈的情感共鸣。
case of Jimmy Lie and democratic
因此，我非常高兴听到首相提及此事。
freedoms in Hong Kong. So, I'm really
他是否愿借此机会……
pleased to hear the prime minister raise
（原文无内容，保持空行）
that. Would he take this opportunity for
the benefit of my constituents to set
为了我选民的利益，我愿再次阐述那些
out again the detail of uh those
讨论的具体内容。
discussions? Uh will he also reassure
他是否也会向他们保证，
them of this country's commitment to
本国对来自香港人士的承诺，
those from Hong Kong who have made their
这些人已经作出了他们的贡献。
home here and that this government will
这里是他们的家园，政府将
listen carefully to their views as part
认真倾听他们的意见，作为内政部关于
of the Home Office's consultation on
有条件定居权咨询的一部分。
earned settlement? Yeah. Yeah.
是的，是的。
>> Prime Minister.
>> 首相。
>> Well, let me give him that reassurance
>> 好的，请允许我向他作出这一保证
for those from Hong Kong in his
对于他选区内以及全国各地的香港同胞，
constituency and across the whole
以及我们将为他们提供的支持，
country and the support that we will put
我们会全力以赴，
in uh for them.
以实际行动予以帮助。
>> John Cooper.
>> 约翰·库珀。
>> Thank you, Madam Deputy Speaker. The SNP
>> 感谢，议长副手女士。苏格兰民族党
Scottish government undertook a
苏格兰政府去年进行了
secretive trip to Beijing last year and
一次秘密的北京之行，期间
caught a case of Ren Mimi fever while
感染了“任密密热”。
they were there. They're now blundering
他们曾经在那里。如今他们在国际舞台上笨拙地挣扎，
around on the world stage desperate for
拼命希望闵阳能向阿迪斯投入资金。
Minyang to put money into Ardis.
尽管如此，首相能否向议会保证，
Notwithstanding the jobs, will the prime
他将……
minister assure the house that he will
（原文未完，无法翻译）
take cognizance of national security
关注国家安全问题。
issues. We do not want jobs at any cost.
我们不希望以任何代价换取就业岗位。
We cannot have wind farms that have
我们不能接受装有中国“杀伤开关”的风电场。
Chinese kill switches fitted.
>> 是的，是的。
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> 是的。是的。
>> Well, as you will have heard me say a
>> 正如您刚才听我所说，
moment ago, no decision has been made
目前尚未做出任何决定。
yet. But um as I outlined in my report
但正如我在向议会提交的报告中所概述的，
back to the house, uh the overarching
我们对所有事务采取的总体方针是，
approach we take to all matters in uh
……
involving um China is that national
涉及中国的问题，国家安全始终是首要考虑。
security always comes first. David
大卫·泰勒。
Taylor.
>> 谢谢您，副议长女士。
>> Thank you, Madame Deputy Speaker. On
我谨代表全党派日本小组，
behalf of the all party group on Japan,
...
can I say a aragato gazyas to the prime
我想对首相访问日本表示衷心感谢，
minister for his visit to Japan and I
并希望他的访问非常顺利愉快。
hope that he had a seagoy time. Um, I
嗯，我想我们全体议员都为
think we are all proud in this house of
GCAP项目感到自豪，该项目具有重要的
the GCAP program which holds a great
意义。
opportunity not only for global,
这不仅是全球、
regional and UK security but also for
区域以及英国安全的机遇，
British jobs. The prime minister
同时也是英国就业的机遇。首相
mentioned that Japan is already one of
提到日本已经是英国的主要投资者之一。请问他
the main investors in the UK. Does he
是否认为…
share my hope that this program, just
我也希望这个项目，
like the Concord program with France all
就像多年前与法国的协和项目一样，
those years ago, will lead to knock-on
能带来连锁反应般的积极影响，
benefits for British jobs and
促进英国就业，
innovations in our economy?
推动我们经济中的创新发展。
>> Prime Minister,
>> 首相，
>> well, can I thank him for his um
>> 好的，我能否感谢他在周末发表的
comments and and his message over the
言论以及传达的信息。
weekend. Um uh Japan is a key NATO ally
日本是北约的重要盟友，
uh a G7 and and of course the coalition
是七国集团成员，当然也是联盟的一部分。
of the willing um and um as he rightly
愿意合作的国家，嗯，正如他正确指出的，
points out um with key investments in
在英国进行关键投资，
the United Kingdom and that's why we
这也是我们讨论所有这些事项的原因，
discussed all those matters and GCAP
以及我们在那里时的全球合作伙伴计划（GCAP）。
when we were there.
当我们在那里的时候。
>> Gregory Stafford.
>> 格雷戈里·斯塔福德。
>> Madame Deputy Speaker, the prime
>> 女副议长，首相提到了他此前在巴西气候大会上与中国国家主席的会晤。
minister mentioned his previous meeting
>> 一天之后，45名支持民主的
with the Chinese president in Brazil at
>> （内容未完，需后续字幕补充）
COP. One day later, 45 pro-democracy
COP。一天后，45名民主派
Hong Kongers were sentenced. Weaggguers,
香港人被判刑。我们看到，
Fallen Gong, Tibetians, unregistered
被打压的香港人、藏人、未注册的
religious groups, human rights lawyers
宗教团体、人权律师
and pro-democracy campaigners, Hong
以及支持民主的活动家，
Kongers in this country, Jimmy Lie. What
在本国的香港人，吉米·赖。什么情况？
single tangible difference has the has
唯一切实的区别是
the prime minister made for their safety
首相为他们的安全
and security?
和保障所做的努力吗？
>> Mr. Speaker, of course there's concerns.
>> 议长先生，当然存在担忧。
They're out in this house. Um they're
这些担忧在本院中广泛存在。
out there. The difference between us is
外界存在分歧。
our position is that the mature serious
我们的立场是，成熟而严肃的做法是
thing to do is to have leaderto leader
进行领导人之间的对话，
discussions about the engage in the
就相关问题展开讨论。
issue. Their approach is to shout about
他们的做法则是大声喧哗，试图引起注意。
the issues, get a bag of sand and put
这些问题，拿一袋沙子把头埋进去，
your head in it and influence absolutely
完全没有任何影响力。
none. It is so unserious. They're not
这实在太不严肃了。
fit for government for many many many
他们在未来许多年里都不适合执政。
years to come.
（无内容，原文结束）
>> Peter swallow.
>> 彼得·斯沃洛先生。
>> Thank you madam deputy speaker. Prime
>> 感谢副议长女士。首相阁下应当知道，
Minister will know uh there are many
有许多日本公司将他们的英国总部设在我选区内，
Japanese companies who have their
…
British home in my constituency in
Bratnull. So can I welcome uh his uh
Bratnull。那么，我能否欢迎他访问日本，
visit to Japan and could he set out a
并请他详细说明一下，
little bit more about how we can
我们如何能够
strengthen our relationship further with
进一步加强与我们日本朋友和盟友的关系，
our Japanese uh friends and allies and
并且……
what that will mean for my constituents?
这对我的选民意味着什么？
Well, can I pay tribute to all those in
我能否向所有那些在他选区内的人致敬，
his constituency of which there are very
正如他所言，他的选区内人数众多，
many as he rightly says enhancing our
正确地指出，加强我们与日本的贸易和经济联系，
trade and economic ties with Japan is in
是符合我们利益的。
the interests of both of our countries
我们两国的利益
and that's precisely what we're focused
这正是我们关注的重点。
on.
>> 布拉德利·托马斯
>> Bradley Thomas
>> 议长，尽管首相已经…
>> speaker while the prime minister has
>> 议长先生，虽然首相已经
failed to stand up for Britain's
未能维护英国的利益
interests from what we've seen he
从我们所见，他甚至无法独自走过北京的红地毯，
couldn't even make it across Beijing's
必须有人引导着前行。
red carpet without being guided along
呃，首相到底想要表达什么？
the way. Uh, what did the prime minister
方式。呃，首相做了什么
expect to receive in return for
期望通过批准中国超级大使馆获得什么回报？
approving the Chinese super embassy? And
中国方面是否给予了他这些回报？
did the Chinese give it to him?
>> 首相，
>> Prime Minister,
>> 我们在本国已经设有一家大使馆，
>> we've had an embassy in this country
...
since 1877.
自1877年以来。
It's currently over seven sites. It's
目前有七个以上的场所。
now going to be on one. The security and
现在将集中到一个场所。安全和情报部门在决定公布的次日发表了一封信，
intelligence services published a letter
以此说明，
the day after the decision to say to say
（内容未完，无法翻译）
that that was uh better for security in
那样对本国安全更有利。
this country. And I think that's the
我认为这是正确的做法。
right approach.
>> 彼得·斯沃勒发言。
>> Peter Swaller.
抱歉，[笑声]
Sorry, [laughter]
>> Chris Bins. Chris Bins second.
>> 克里斯·宾斯。克里斯·宾斯附议。
>> Thank you, Madam Deputy Speaker, and can
>> 感谢您，副议长女士，我能否感谢首相今天的声明以及他持续的国际领导力？
I thank the prime minister for his
>> 我知道，
statement today and his continued
>> （此处原文未完，无法翻译）
international leadership? I know,
however, wherever he goes in the work
然而，无论他走到世界的哪个角落，
world, he's always thinking about
他总是在想着哈洛。
Harlow. Um, can I ask the prime
请问首相，
minister, what difference will a
建立富有成效的关系将带来什么样的变化？
productive relationship make with the
与……之间的关系？
second largest economy and our third
作为世界第二大经济体和我们的第三大贸易伙伴，
biggest trading partner make to
他为我的职位上的企业带来了什么贡献？
businesses in my posit?
他是哈洛的坚定支持者，我曾多次访问那里，感到非常欣慰。
uh he's a champion of for Harlow and it
呃，他是哈洛（Harlow）的捍卫者，
was so good to visit so many times. Um
很高兴能多次访问那里。嗯
we had 60 businesses on the delegation
我们的代表团中有60家企业随行。
with us. They were enthusiastic about
他们对此次访问将为他们带来的机遇充满热情，
the opportunities that this visit would
以及所有相关的商业机会，
open up for them and all the associated
包括他的选区内的企业。
businesses including his constituency
包括他选区的企业
that will be able to uh work with them
将能够与他们合作
on projects in the future.
开展未来的项目。
>> Dr. Luke Evans,
>> 卢克·埃文斯博士，
>> it's widely reported in the media that
>> 媒体广泛报道，
the prime minister and his entourage had
首相及其随行人员曾经…
burner phones when they went across to
他们前往中国时使用了一次性手机。
China. Could he confirm this? And if it
他能否确认这一点？如果确认，
is confirmed, was the reason because he
原因是否因为他担心自己被监视？
was worried he was being spied upon?
>> 首相。
>> Prime Minister.
>> Madame Deputy Speaker, we we we took uh
>> 女议长女士，我们我们我们采取了
appropriate precautions as we do
适当的预防措施，就像我们访问任何国家时一样。
whichever country we visit.
>> 约翰·斯林格。
>> John Slinger.
>> 谢谢您，女议长女士。就像…
>> Thank you, Madam Deputy Speaker. Like
>> 谢谢您，副议长女士。像
the Prime Minister, I'm a musician and a
首相先生，我是一名音乐家，同时也是创意艺术领域的坚定支持者。
strong advocate for the creative arts
因此，您能否向议会详细说明，
sector. So could he set out to the house
为什么您会采取如此多的措施针对创意艺术和文化组织，
a little more why he took so many
并对这些组织产生如此大的影响？
creative arts and cultural organizations
（原文第5条不完整，无法翻译）
with him to China? And does he agree
他是否愿意与他一道前往中国？他是否同意
that Britain is the best in the world at
英国在创意艺术领域是世界领先的？
the creative arts? It's good for trade.
这对贸易有利。
It's good for jobs. It's good for our
这对就业有利。
young people particularly. And the kind
这尤其对我们的年轻人有利。
of visit he's been on will help help
他此次访问所带来的帮助将会有所助益，
with this as will investment at home and
国内外的投资同样如此。
abroad.
>> 我感谢他提出的问题。我同意他的看法。我们是最优秀的，嗯，在……
>> I uh thank him for his question. I agree
>> 我感谢他的提问。我同意
with him. We are the best um in the
他的观点。我们是最好的，嗯，在
world and the uh creative sector those
世界以及创意产业那些
um from the cultural institutions were
来自文化机构的人士
with us um on the visit because they
随我们一同访问，
could see the great advantage in better
因为他们能够看到更好关系和更紧密合作的巨大优势，
relations and better engagement um not
并非...
only in relation to the cultural aspects
仅限于文化方面
but of course they are in themselves
但当然，它们本身
really important businesses.
就是非常重要的企业。
>> Dan Krueer.
>> 丹·克鲁尔。
>> Thank you very much madam deputy
>> 非常感谢，副议长女士。
speaker. The prime minister is very full
议长。首相非常强调
of the abstract virtue of engaging with
与中国接触的抽象美德，
China and getting in the room with them.
以及与中国同桌协商的重要性。
He used to say that Britain shouldn't
他过去曾说，英国甚至不应该
even sign a trade deal with China
与中国签署贸易协议。
because of the persecution of the
因为对维吾尔族人民的迫害。
weaguer people. So having now got in the
既然已经与中国领导人同处一室，
room with the Chinese leader, can he
他能否告诉议会，
tell the house a single thing that he
他代表维吾尔族人民
achieved on behalf of the weaguers or
取得了哪怕一项成果？
indeed on behalf of the security of this
确实是为了本国的安全，
country?
吗？
>> Prime Minister.
>> 首相。
>> Yes, engaging is really important for
>> 是的，积极参与对于本国安全非常重要。并且，呃，
the security of this country. And uh
这个国家的安全。而且呃
just for clarity, we didn't sign a trade
为了澄清，我们并未在此次访问中签署贸易协议。
deal uh on the uh visit. We simply uh
我们只是探讨了如何为企业开拓更多机遇的途径。
looked at the ways in which we can open
当时有60家大型企业随行，
the opportunities for businesses. There
一同参与了相关讨论。
were 60 big businesses with us um on the
（原文第5条不完整，无法翻译）
visit and they're absolutely clear about
访问期间，他们对所获益处非常清楚，
the advantages to them and I'd much
我更愿意采纳他们对这些优势的看法，
rather take their view on the advantages
而不是采信本院另一方所散布的无稽之谈。
um than the nonsense that's being
相比之下，
spouted on the other side of this house.
议会另一边喷出的废话。
>> Harriet Cross.
>> 哈丽雅特·克罗斯。
>> Thank you madam deputy speaker. China is
>> 感谢副议长女士。中国正通过影子船队和俄罗斯石油资助俄罗斯对乌克兰的战争。
helping to fund Russia's war on Ukraine
>> 首相能否……
via the shadow fleet and Russian oil.
通过影子船队和俄罗斯石油。
Firstly, can the prime minister an
首先，首相能否
unamiguously confirm that he mentioned
明确确认他提到了
and brought up Russian oil and their
并提出了俄罗斯石油及其
shadow fleet because it's not mentioned
影子船队的问题，因为声明中并未具体提及。
specifically in the statement. And
其次，中国现在将采取哪些措施
secondly, what steps will China now take
来应对这一情况？
to end their importation of Russian oil,
结束他们对俄罗斯石油的进口，
which is funding death and destruction
因为这助长了乌克兰的死亡与破坏。
across Ukraine.
>> 是的，说得好。
>> Yeah. Well said.
>> 这是一个非常重要的问题，
>> Well, this is a really important issue
>> 嗯，这是一个非常重要的问题
and that's why I had a phone call with
这就是为什么我在离开前一天与
uh Florio Zalinski the day before the
弗洛里奥·扎林斯基进行了电话通话。
day before I left. I'll have a further
我回国后还将与他进行进一步讨论，
discussion with him uh when I get back
并且我在……中提出了这一问题，
and that I I raised the issue uh in
……
terms uh during the course of the visit.
访问期间的条款等事项。
>> Charlie Duhurst speaker and and further
>> 查理·杜赫斯特，议长，进一步补充一点，
to that point, ch Russia has been able
俄罗斯能够做到这一点，
to triple its ballistic missile
是因为它的弹道导弹生产能力已经增加了三倍，
production because it has access to
这得益于它获得了……
Chinese rocket fuel. It has access to
中国火箭燃料。它能够获得
Chinese machine tools and it has access
中国的机床设备，并且能够获得
to Chinese microprocessors. In return,
中国的微处理器。作为回报，
China is receiving vast quantities of
中国获得了大量的
discounted oil, gas, aluminium, other
折扣石油、天然气、铝以及其他资源。
natural resources. is China is quite
自然资源。中国实际上是在为乌克兰战争提供燃料。
literally fueling the war in Ukraine. So
所以，
can I ask the prime minister once again
我能否再次请教首相，
what specific guarantees did he receive
他从中国政府那里获得了哪些具体保证，
from the Chinese government that they
这些保证是指他们……
would work to deescalate the conflict in
将致力于缓解乌克兰的冲突
Ukraine?
？
>> The the reason I spoke to Vladimir
>> 我与弗拉基米尔·泽连斯基通话的原因是，
Zinsky was to um have a discussion with
嗯，事先与他进行讨论，正是为了，呃，
him in advance as precisely uh the terms
明确相关条款
in which we would approach this issue. I
关于我们将如何处理这一问题。
then followed through on that and I will
随后我付诸行动，
talk to President Zensky again uh in
并将在未来几天再次与泽连斯基总统进行会谈，
coming days uh about this. We're working
我们正与乌克兰方面紧密合作，
handin glove with the Ukrainians for the
齐心协力推进相关工作。
outcome that we all want, which is just
我们都期望的结果，那就是公正而持久的和平。
and lasting peace.
>> 谢农，副议长，我能否感谢首相的声明？
>> Shannon, Deputy Speaker, can I thank the
同时，我欢迎首相此次成功的贸易访问。
prime minister for his statement? And I
首相的声明？我
welcome the PM successful trade missions
欢迎首相成功的贸易代表团
to China and Japan. In particular, I'm
对中国和日本。特别是，
heartened by the strides made in
我对日方合作取得的进展感到鼓舞。
Japanese cooperation. However, I would
然而，我希望了解
like to ascertain what steps forward
在中方方面取得了哪些具体进展，
were made in terms of the Chinese
以及在什么步骤上有所推进。
treatment of Christians, of weaguer
对基督徒的待遇，对维吾尔族人的待遇，
Muslims, of fallen gong and other
对穆斯林、对法轮功以及其他宗教少数群体的待遇，
religious minorities and how the prime
以及首相如何能够利用外交软实力
minister was able to use uh diplomatic
推动这些改变，
soft power to bring about the changes
。
required for to stop human rights or to
需要采取措施以制止侵犯人权行为，
provide human rights protection and to
保障人权保护，
stop religious pre prison persecution
终止宗教迫害，
and successful trade between the two
促进两国之间的成功贸易。
names and two nations. Thank you.
谢谢大家。
right to raise these um really important
有权提出这些非常重要的问题，
um issues and that's uh why I raised
这也是我在访问期间亲自提出这些问题的原因，
them myself during the course of the
并且我感谢他。
visit and I thank him
>> 以上陈述到此结束。我将…
>> and that concludes the statement. I'll
>> 声明到此结束。我将
give a few moments for the front benches
请给前排席位几分钟时间进行更换。
to swap over.
让前排席位的议员们交换位置。